<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The meane in mourning. A sermon preached at Saint Maryes Spittle in London on Tuesday in Easter weeke. 1595. / By Thomas Playfere Doctor of Diuinitie.</title>
            <author>Playfere, Thomas, 1561?-1609.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1596</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 164 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 68 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00565</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20015</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S94747</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52633331</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52633331</idno>
            <idno type="VID">174760</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00565)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 174760)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2124:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The meane in mourning. A sermon preached at Saint Maryes Spittle in London on Tuesday in Easter weeke. 1595. / By Thomas Playfere Doctor of Diuinitie.</title>
                  <author>Playfere, Thomas, 1561?-1609.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 120 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the Widow Orwin for Andrew Wise, dwelling in Paules Church yeard, at the sign of the Angel.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1596.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [8].</note>
                  <note>Also published with title: A most excellent and heauenly sermon vpon the 23 chapter of the gospell by Saint Luke--Cf. STC (2nd ed.) and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴, B-H⁸, I⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references in marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Luke XXIII --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:174760:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE MEANE IN MOVRNING.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> Sermon preached at Saint Maryes <hi>Spittle in London on Tueſday in Easter weeke.</hi> 1595.</p>
            <p>By THOMAS PLAYFERE Doctor of Diuinitie.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by the Widow Orwin for Andrew Wiſe, <hi>dwelling in Paules Church yeard, at the ſigne of the Angel.</hi> 1596.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:174760:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174760:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE AND MOST VIRTVOVS LADY, the Lady <hi>Elizabeth Carey,</hi> wife to the thriſe-noble, Sir <hi>George Carey,</hi> Knight Marſhall, &amp;c. all proſperitie and happines.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Adam, it is reported that <hi>Demonax</hi> hauing his head broken with a ſtone, and being aduiſed to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine to the Proconſull of that iniurie, anſwered that hee had more neede goe to a ſurgeon to heale his head, then to a Magiſtrate to redreſſe his wrong. I must alſo confeſſe, I had rather haue had my head broken, then my ſermon ſo mangled. For this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon hath been twiſe printed already without my procurement or priuitie any manner of way. Yea to my very great griefe and trouble. Neuertheles I haue
<pb facs="tcp:174760:3"/>thought good to complaine of no man. For in whom the fault reſteth I cannot learne certainely. This I am ſure, not any whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in my ſelfe. <hi>Clinius</hi> a Historiographer, hauing written the ſtory of <hi>Virginius,</hi> and meeting with him vpon a time ſaide, If you find any thing amiſſe in your ſtory, I pray you pardon it. To whom <hi>Virginius</hi> anſwered, What <hi>Clinius,</hi> doest thou not know I haue done as I did, that ſuch fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes as thou art, might write as you would? And ſo, it was my part, to take ſuch paynes as conueniently I could, is furniſhing and prouiding this ſermon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the appoynted time. But afterward what others, eyther by reporting or prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting would make of it, that was not my fault, that was not in me either to helpe or hinder. Therefore I haue not gone vnto any Magiſtrate to complaine, but though it be one of the greateſt iniuries that euer was offered mee, yet becauſe I knowe not what ſecret purpoſe the Lord had in lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this affliction vpon me, I doe moſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly pardon it. Yea, euen as <hi>Moyſes,</hi> when the first tables were broken, was content to make new: in like manner, finding in the first editions ſo many bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken-ended
<pb facs="tcp:174760:3"/>ſentences, I haue as it were gone to a ſurgeon, or rather in deede I haue played the ſurgeon my ſelfe, and by ſetting out the ſermon a new, haue ſalued the matter as well as I could. <hi>Diogenes</hi> ſeeing the city of <hi>Myndus</hi> very little and poore, but the gate thereof very large and ſtately, ſayd, You of <hi>Myndus,</hi> ſhut your gate, and keepe in your citie, that it runne not away. After the ſame ſorte, the gate (as I may ſay) and the firſt entrance into this Sermon, was before very lofty and ſtately, the Sermon it ſelfe very ſimple and poore. Such a ſtirre they kept, in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it very vainely and moſt fondly, <hi>A moſt excellent Sermon,</hi> as if they would haue caſt the houſe out of the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, or the citie out of the gate. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I haue made the gate leſſer, and the citie greater. The gate leſſer, by entitling it, <hi>The meane in Mourning,</hi> which is the very drift in deede, and the right ſcope of the whole Sermon. And the citie greater, by adding diuers notes, in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry places of the Sermon, as I haue ſince thought beſt. So that if any which heard it preached be diſpoſed to reade it, he ſhall not, I hope, altogether loſe his labour. For
<pb facs="tcp:174760:4"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:174760:4"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:174760:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:174760:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:174760:6"/>though hee haue all heere which he heard then, yet hee heard not all then, which he hath heere. But how it will pleaſe God to affect others I know not. This I wot well, that many a time and oft I haue beene much mooued my ſelfe with the medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſome poyntes in this Sermon. And now of late, next to God and to his holy word, I could take comfort in nothing ſo much, as in reading that which I haue written in the ſeuenth part, the firſt ſecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof. Occaſioned thereto, by the certaine report of the death of my most deare father, who was well knowne, for his place and calling, to be as good a man, and as ſincere a chriſtian, as any hath li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in this age. But for concluſion, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly deſire your Ladiſhip, that as I haue dedicated the <hi>Pathway to Perfection</hi> to my very Honorable good patron, Sir <hi>George Carey:</hi> ſo it would pleaſe your Ladiſhip, to let this Sermon paſſe vnder the countenance and credit of your name. For if your Ladiſhip will deigne to reade it ouer, then I doubt not but diuers other Ladies &amp; Gentlewomen, which haue vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and noble mindes, will vouchſafe alſo to learne thereby, how they ought
<pb facs="tcp:174760:6"/>with the daughters of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> not to weepe for Christ, but to weepe for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. Especially, hauing ſuch a ſingular enſample before their eyes as your Ladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is, whom God hath endued with al or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments &amp; gifts, both of nature &amp; grace.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From Saint Iohns Colledge in Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge
<date>the firſt day of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary. <hi>1595.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline> 
               <signed>Your Ladyſhips euer to be commaunded, Thomas Playfere.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:174760:7"/>
            <list>
               <head>Faults in all the Copies.</head>
               <item>p. 24. l. 19. for licked reade licked vp</item>
               <item>p. 62. l. 23. for ſetler reade ſetter</item>
               <item>p. 67. l. 28. for too to reade too</item>
               <item>p. 71. l. 23. for Noah reade Noahs</item>
               <item>p. 80. l. 28. for ſayes. reade ſayes,</item>
               <item>p. 99. l. 25. for man reade men</item>
               <item>p. 107. l. 14 for Lord: reade Lord.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Faults in ſome of the Copies.</head>
               <item>p. 6. l. 17. for thoſe read theſe</item>
               <item>p. 7. l. 12. for rogy read rogly</item>
               <item>p. 33. l. 8. for ran read run</item>
               <item>p. 39. l. 24. for holy read hot</item>
               <item>p. 53. l. 21. for Chriſt. read Chriſt,</item>
               <item>p. 63. l. 16. for bands read hands</item>
               <item>p. 92. l. 2. for age read age, and</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:174760:7"/>
            <head>THE MEANE IN MOVR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NING.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>The Text.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>Weepe not for mee, but weepe for your ſelues.</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Luk. 23.28.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable, right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull, and moſt Chriſtian and bleſſed brethren; foure ſortes of people were about Chriſt, when Chriſt was about his paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Of the firſt ſorte were <hi>executioners,</hi> which tormented him. Of the ſecond ſorte were <hi>Iewes</hi> which mock't him. Of the third ſorte were <hi>lookers-on,</hi> which mark't him. Of the fourth ſorte were <hi>wel-willers,</hi> which lamented him. Now al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be very likely, that amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g theſe
<pb facs="tcp:174760:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:174760:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:174760:9"/>his <hi>wel-willers,</hi> diuers godly men wept for him, as Saint Iohn the Euangeliſt, Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph of Arimathia, Gamaliell, Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus, and ſuch like; yet it is certaine, both that more women wept then men, and that the women more wept then the men. <hi>More women: more weeping. More women</hi> wept then men, partly by the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of men, who thought that the womens weeping came rather from weaknes in themſelues, then from kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes towards Chriſt. Partly by the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, who ſuffered <hi>more women</hi> to weepe then men, that the women, which bewailed Chriſtes death, might condemne the men, which procured it. Now the women alſo <hi>more wept</hi> then the men, either of a naturall affection, or els of a voluntary diſpoſition. Naturally ſayth S. Peter, the woman is the weaker veſſel,<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Theophylact. in Iohan. ca. <hi>20.</hi> pag. <hi>571.</hi>
               </note> ſoone moued to weepe, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to many, either affectionate paſſions or els paſſionate affections. But touching theſe women, that which was otherwiſe naturall to them, was here voluntary in them. For the ſinne of a woman, was the ruine of man. Therefore theſe women willingly <hi>wept the more.</hi> That though a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:174760:9"/>woman did moſt in the ſecond death of the firſt Adam; yet theſe might doe leaſt in the firſt death of the ſecond Adam. For it was Eue a woman which betrayed the firſt Adam with an apple, &amp; cauſed him to ſin; but it was Iudas a man which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed the ſecond Adam with a kiſſe, and cauſed him to die. And indeed you ſhal generally obſerue, that notwithſtanding at the firſt, the woman went before the man in tranſgreſſion and diſobedience, neuertheleſſe ſince to make amends for that fault, the bleſſed Virgine Mary, and diuers other women haue farre excelled all men, or at the leaſt wiſe, moſt men, in true deuotion and godlines. Wherefore principally Chriſt here ſpeaketh to the women, becauſe both <hi>more women</hi> wept then men; &amp; the women alſo <hi>more wept</hi> then the men; <hi>more wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; more weeping;</hi> but yet in them he ſpeaketh (as wel as to them) indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to al his deere friends, both men and women, VVEEPE NOT FOR ME, BVT VVEEPE FOR YOVR SELVES.</p>
            <p>In which ſentence wee may obſerue, as many wordes ſo many partes. Eyght words: eight partes. The firſt, VVEEPE NOT: the ſecond, BVT VVEEPE: the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:174760:10"/>third, VVEEPE NOT, BVT VVEEPE: the fourth, FOR MEE: the fift, FOR YOVR SELVES: the ſixt, FOR ME, FOR YOVR SELVES. The ſeuenth, VVEEPE NOT FOR ME; the eight, BVT VVEEPE FOR YOVR SELVES. God grant all our hearts may be ſo affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with the conſideration of theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent matters, as may make moſt for the increaſe of our comfort in him, and his glory in vs. And I humbly beſeech you alſo moſt chriſtian brethren, to doe God this honor, and me this fauour. Firſt that you would not preſcribe mee anie methode, or order, how I ſhould handle this text, but that you would giue mee leaue to follow mine own methode, and order, wherein I perſwade my ſelfe, and I hope alſo truly, I haue bin directed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit of God. Secondly, that you would not run before me, in your ſwift conceit, &amp; earneſt expectation, but that it would pleaſe you to goe on along eaſily all the way with me, till happily at the length, by Gods gracious aſſiſtance, and your gentle acceptance, I come to the end of my Sermon. And then if I haue omitted any thing, which you would haue had
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:174760:10"/>me ſayd, ſpare mee not, but blame me hardly for it, as you ſhall thinke beſt. VVEEPE NOT FOR ME, BVT VVEEP FOR YOVR SELVES.</p>
            <p>THe firſt part is, VVEEPE NOT. When lairus the ruler of the ſinagogue wept bitterly for the death of his daughter; Chriſt ſaid vnto him,<note n="b" place="margin">Luk. c. 8.52.</note>
               <hi>weepe not.</hi> When Rachel wept, and would not be comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſeeing neither her ſonne Beniamin, nor almoſt any true Beniamite left aliue; God ſayd vnto her,<note n="c" place="margin">Ier. c. 31.16.</note>
               <hi>weepe not.</hi> When a poore widow wept ſore for the death of her onely ſonne, Chriſt ſayde vnto her,<note n="d" place="margin">Luk. 7.15.</note>
               <hi>weep not,</hi> And ſo here, Chriſt ſeeing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Iairuſſes, many Rachels, many wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, weepe for the death of the onely ſonne of God, ſayeth vnto them, <hi>weepe not.</hi> Forbidding thereby immoderate weeping, which is condemned, <hi>in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; in reaſon; in religion. In nature,</hi> the earth when it reioyceth, as in the ſummer time then it is couered with corne,<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 65.12.</note> but when it hath to too forlorne, &amp; ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full a countenance, as in the winter time, then it is fruitleſſe, and barren. The water when it is quiet, and calme, bringeth in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:174760:11"/>all maner of marchandiſe, but when the ſea ſtormes, and roares too much, then the very ſhippes do houle and crie<note n="f" place="margin">Eſay. 23.1.</note> The ayre looking cleerely, and cheerefully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſheth all thinges, but weeping too much, that is, rayning too much, as in Noahs floude, it drownes the whole world. The fire being but a little ſpri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kled with water burneth more brightly, but being too much ouerwhelmed, it giues neither heate, nor light. The eye it ſelfe (as Anatomiſts write)<note n="(g)" place="margin">Vide Veſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium. lib. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>14</hi> &amp; Toletum in lib. ſecund. Aristotelis de anima.</note> hath twiſe as many drie skins, like ſluces, to dam vp the courſe of the teares, as it hath moyſt humours, like channels, to let them flow forth. For it hath ſixe of them, and but three of thoſe. If al the body were an eye, and there were no eares in it: where were then the hearing? If all the eye were a moyſt humour, and there were no drye skins in it, where were then the ſeeing? Seeing then too much weeping is; in the earth barrennes; in the water ſhip wrack; in the aire an inundation; in the fire cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; in the eye blindnes; certainely if, the earth, the water, the ayre, the fire, the eie, could ſpeak, they would altogether with one concent ſing a ioyfull ſong of fiue
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:174760:11"/>parts, and euery one ſeuerally ſay vnto vs, That we muſt not weepe too much.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>reaſon</hi> ſeeth yet more,<note n="(h)" place="margin">Ne quid nimit.</note> That too much of a thing is nought. <hi>Etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mel, ſi ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ingratu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Which is tranſlated thus,<note n="i" place="margin">Prouer. 25.27</note> It is not good to eate too much honie. If it bee not good eating too much honie; then ſure it is not good eating too much wormewood. The Egyptians when they would deſcribe teares, they paint thoſe gems, which we call vnions, whereupon Suidas ſayth,<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Vnions hierogyphically do ſignifie the ſhedding of teares. For as vnions haue their name in latine, becauſe they are found one by one, &amp; neuer more at once: ſo teares muſt be ſhed eaſily one by one, and neuer bee powred out all at once. Seneca ſayeth, that which we muſt do dayly, we muſt do moderately. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though we can not quite ſtop the bloudy iſſue of our teares, at the leaſtwiſe we muſt be ſparing, &amp; weep ſo to day, as we may weepe to morrow, &amp; keep ſome teares awaies in ſtore, reſeruing<note n="l" place="margin">Si non finire lachrymas, at certè reſeruare debemus. l. de conſolatio. ad Polybiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> c. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> them to another occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> afterward. For we reade that Heraclitus when he had ſook't and ſowſt himſelfe in ſorrow all his liſe long, at length dyed of a dropſie, and ſo (as I
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:174760:12"/>may ſay) drowned himſelfe in his owne teares. Yea Niobe by ouermuch wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping was turnde into a ſtone; euen as Lots wife by turning backe, was turnde into ſalt. It was one of Pythagoras poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies,<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> not to eate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hart; which is expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thus,<note n="n" place="margin">Prou. 25.20.</note> As a moath freateth the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and a worme eateth the wood: ſo heauines hurteth ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s hart. Now if we may not teare the hart of any otherthing with our teeth, then much leſſe may we teare our owne hart, with our teares. So that eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> blind reaſon, ſuch as the heathen haue had, doth yet plainely ſee this, That we muſt not weepe too much.</p>
            <p>But <hi>religion</hi> goeth yet further. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God at the firſt placed ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the garden of Eden, which is the garden of pleaſure, he did indeede there prouide all thinges for him, which might pleaſure him. His wife which was equall to him: all other creatures that were inferiour to him: the hearbes which hee did eate: the flowers that he did ſmell: the pearles which hee did look vpon: the gold that he did tread vpon: all theſe ſerude for his delight and ioy. Afterward when ſentence had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded againſt the man, that hee ſhould
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:174760:12"/>haue ſorrow about the fruit of the earth, againſt the woman, that ſhe ſhould haue ſorrowe about the fruite of the wombe, yet it pleaſed God to aſſwage and ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten theſe our ſorrowes with diuerſe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular comforts. As firſt, we haue the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirit, who is the only comforter. Next a good conſcience, which is a continuall feaſt. Then the holy ſcripture, which is (as it were) an other paradiſe. Laſtly, an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained faith by which wee haue peace with GOD. Therefore Athenagoras<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. l. de reſur. mor.</note> ſayes well, I count that they haue no ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, no conſcience, no ſcripture, no faith in them which yeeld to too much griefe. And Hierome yet more vehemently,<note n="p" place="margin">Deteſt andae ſunt iſtae la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrymae quae no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> habent modu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> I doe from my hart deteſt al exceſſiue ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, ſeeing it is a very hell vpon earth, and an entrance euen in this life into that wofull place where there is nothing but weeping and gnaſhing of teeth. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore immoderate weeping is condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>in nature,</hi> which teacheth al things: <hi>in reaſon,</hi> which teacheth all men: <hi>in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> which teacheth al chriſtians, That wee muſt not weepe too much. Thus much of weeping too much, which is the firſt part, VVEEPE NOT. WEEPE
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:174760:13"/>NOT FOR ME, BVT VVEEPE FOR YOVR SELVES.</p>
            <p>NOwe a little of weeping too little which is the ſecond parte, BVT VVEEPE. They to whom Chriſt heere ſpeaketh, offended in th'exceſſe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he beginneth thus, <hi>weepe not.</hi> But I may wel ſhift the words, and begin thus, <hi>But weepe.</hi> For wee offend, commonly in the wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of weeping, ſeldome in th'xe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe. The reaſon is, becauſe wee lacke loue, which being three folde; towardes our ſelues: towards our neighbour: to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God; the greateſt worke of loue; towards our ſelues is <hi>repentance:</hi> towards our neighbour is <hi>preaching:</hi> towardes God is <hi>praier.</hi> And al theſe require ſome teares. So that if we weepe ſo little as that we weepe not at all, we weepe too little. Which we muſt not doe. For firſt, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching <hi>repentance</hi> one ſayes truely,<note n="q" place="margin">Hoc ipſo ſunt maiores tumo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, quò mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris dolores.</note> The leſſer our ſorrowes are, the greater are our ſinnes. But on th' other ſide, the heads of dragons are broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the waters<note n="r" place="margin">Pſalm. 74.13.</note> that is, very ſtrong and vile ſinnes are weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and waſht away with teares. That obligation which was againſt vs<note n="f" place="margin">Colloſ. 2.14.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:174760:13"/>it had beene faſtned to the croſte of Chriſt was engroſſed in parchme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Now it is but ſcribled in paper. So that if wee blur it dayly with weeping vpon it, our teares wil be like <hi>aqua fortis,</hi> to take out the hand-writing quite and cleane, that God ſhall neither reade nor ſee our ſins. When Alexander had reade a long and tedious Epiſtle written to him by Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pater, wherein were diuers accuſations againſt his mother Olympias, What, ſaies he, me thinkes Antipater knoweth not, that one little teare of a mother will eaſily blot out many Epiſtles.<note n="(*)" place="margin">Ignorare videtur Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pater quòd vna matris lachry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma multas de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebit epistolas.</note> And certainely the teares not onely of Gods mother, but euen of euery child of God will much more eaſily blot out the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of many ſinnes, though they were before, like the ſinnes of Iuda, written with a pen of yron, and grauen with the point of a diamond<note n="(*)" place="margin">Iere. 17.1.</note> Therefore ſayth Alcuinus,<note n="t" place="margin">Lauandum est cor poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiae lachry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis.</note> we muſt waſh our hearts in the troubled poole of Betheſda<note n="(u)" place="margin">Iohn. 5.2.</note> in the troubled teares of repentance. For as in a well, except there be ſome water in it we can not eaſily ſee the baggage that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the bottome: ſo in the depth of the heart without teares we can not ſee our
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:174760:14"/>ſinnes. Teares make our ſinnes not ſeene, and ſeene. Not ſeene to God, and ſeene to vs. God not ſeeing them forgiues them, and we ſeeing them amend them. Pliny writeth that the teares of vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branches doe cure the leproſie.<note n="x" place="margin">l. <hi>23.</hi> initio.</note> And ſo the teares of thoſe vine branches which are grafted into the true vine, doe cure the leproſie of ſinne. S. Auſtin witneſſeth that the Eagle feeling his wings heauie, plungeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a fountaine, &amp; ſo renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his ſtrength<note n="y" place="margin">Commen. in Pſal. <hi>103.</hi>
               </note>: After the ſame ſort, a Chriſtian feeling the heauie burthen of his ſins, batheth himſelfe in a fountaine of teares, and ſo waſhing of the olde man, which is the body of ſinne, is made young againe, and luſtie as an eagle. That ſinfull woman<note n="(z)" place="margin">Luk. 7.44.</note> becauſe ſhee lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued much, therefore ſhe waſht Chriſtes feete with her teares. A ſtrange ſight. I haue oftentimes ſeene the heauen waſh the earth. But I neuer before ſawe the earth waſh the heauen: yet here I ſee it. An earthly and a ſinfull woman waſheth the heauenly feete of Chriſt. But becauſe ſhee waſht Chriſts feete with her teares, therefore Chriſt crowned her head with his mercies. The prodigall childe had
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:174760:14"/>no ſooner returned home by weeping croſſe (as we ſay) and cryed <hi>peccaui,</hi> but ſtraightwaies he was receiued. Loe yee whatforce there is in three ſillables.<note n="a" place="margin">Quantum valent tres ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labae? Ambro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius.</note> For God hearing a ſinner in trew contrition vtter but this one word of three ſillables, <hi>peccaui,</hi> I haue ſinned,<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Chryſoſt. Hom. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> is ſo in a maner charmed and inchaunted with it, that he hath no power ouer himſelfe, he cannot but grant remiſſion. Saint Peter likewiſe though he were an old man in yeares, yet he was a very child, and a prodigall child in weeping. And as his faith was ſo great that he lept into a ſea of waters to come to Chriſt: ſo his repentance was ſo great that he lept into a ſea of teares when hee went from Chriſt. He wept ſo bitterly (as Clemens Romanus teſtifieth) that there were gutters and furrowes in his face, made with thoſe teares which trickled downe his cheekes. And therefore ſayes Cyril,<note n="c" place="margin">Locum flendo recepit quem negando perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derat. In Leui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticum. lib. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> hee recouered that place by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayling his offence which hee had loſt by denying his maſter. For ſayth Nazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anzen,<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> God is more merciful, then man can bee ſinfull, if hee will bee ſorrowfull. Wherefore we may ſee by theſe exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, of the ſinfull woman: of the prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:174760:15"/>childe: of Saint Peter, that weeping doth eſpecially recommend our repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, that we may purchaſe our pardon.</p>
            <p>Touching <hi>preaching,</hi> the voyce of a preacher ought to be the voyce of a cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, which ſhould not pype to make the people daunce, but mourne to make them weepe. Hence it is, that in the olde lawe<note n="e" place="margin">Leuit. 21.20.</note> none that was blinde or had any blemiſh in his eye might ſerue at the aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. There are many reaſons of this lawe. Among many this may be one, becauſe for that impediment in his eye hee could not well ſhew his inward ſorrowing by his outward weeping. And when they offered vp to the Lorde their firſt borne, who was ordinarily in euery familie their prieſt or their preacher, they offered alſo with him a paire of turtle doues or two yong pigeons. That paire of turtle doues did ſignifie a paire of mournefull eies. Theſe two yong pigeons did ſignify like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe two weeping eyes. And at that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering they praied for their firſt born, that afterward he might haue ſuch eyes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. For as pigeons flie to their win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes<note n="f" place="margin">Eſay 60.8.</note>: ſo the ſincere preacher hath no other refuge to flie vnto, but onely to his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:174760:15"/>windowes, that is to his eyes, which are glazed with teares, when they weepe for the ſins of the people. Chriſt Ieſus is much delighted in ſuch kinde of eyes, ſaying ſo ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his ſpouſe, Thine eies are pigeons eyes. The holy Ghoſt alſo, deſcending himſelfe in the forme of doue. And the Prophets like doues vpon the waters which are waſht with milke &amp; remaine by the ful veſſels<note n="(g)" place="margin">Cant. 5.12.</note> vſually receiued their prophecies beſide riuers. As Ezechiel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the riuer Cobar: Daniel beſide the riuer Tigris: the Baptiſt beſide the riuer lordane. Yea alſo they preached their prophecies, not ſo much with wordes as with riuers of teares. The prophet Dauid was ſo valiant, that he ouercame a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie huge giant, and tare a Beare in peeces as eaſily as if it had beene a Kyd, &amp; ſlew a fierce lyon with no other weapon, but onely with his naked handes, and diuerſe other times like a violent whirlewinde bare downe all before him. Yet when he came to preach, hee was ſo ſoft-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſo tender-ey'd, that he ſaid, Mine eies guſh out riuers of water, becauſe men keepe not thy law. O that my head were full of water, ſayes Ieremie, &amp; mine
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:174760:16"/>eies a fountaine of teares. I proteſt, ſayes Paule, that for theſe three yeares I haue not ceaſed to warne euery one of you with teares day and night. For indeede, as Auſtin witneſſeth, there is more good to be done with ſighing then with ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, with weeping then with wordes<note n="h" place="margin">Plus gemiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, quàm ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monibus, plus fletu quàm af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatu.</note>. And Proſper ſaith, that a preacher muſt ſeeke not his owne praiſe, but the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples profit in ſorrowing for their ſinnes<note n="i" place="margin">Non plauſum ſed planctum.</note>. And Ierome ſayes, that the preacher is moſt highly commended, not when the people<note n="k" place="margin">Sint eorum lachrymae, tuae laudes.</note> clap their hands, but when they knocke their breaſts. Wherefore as it is an Idol and no God which hath eies and ſeeth not: So hee is rather an Idoll ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard then a godly paſtour, which hath eies and weepeth not more or leſſe, one time or other in preaching to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>Touching <hi>prayer,</hi> Saint Iames ſayes, the prayer of a iuſt man preuaileth much, if it be feruent. For a feruent prayer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from a feruent ſpirit, which is who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſpired with that holy ſpirit, who ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth requeſt in vs and for vs, with ſighes and grones, which cannot be expreſſed. As it is in one of the Pſalmes,<note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 147.18.</note> Hee <hi>ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:174760:16"/>forth his word and melteth them, he bretheth forth his ſpirite, and the waters flowe. Hee ſendeth forth his worde, and breatheth forth his ſpirit,</hi> when the holy Ghoſt moueth vs to praye. <hi>he melteth them and the waters flow,</hi> when teares trickle downe from our eyes. For as a ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing pot runneth ouer: ſo ſayes a holy heart, ſeething (as it were) like a pot, and boyling in feruent prayer<note n="m" place="margin">Pſalm. 42.4.</note>, I power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer my ſoule within mee. According to that of Auſtin<note n="n" place="margin">Quo quiſque ſanctior, eò eius in orando fletus vberior.</note> The more holy and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout a man is, the more will he be ſure to weepe in his prayer. And no maruaile that hee doth weepe in praying, which doth pray for weeping. Grant, O Lorde, ſayes the ſame father, that I may haue a fountaine of teares, then eſpecially when I offer vp to thee my prayers and ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations<note n="o" place="margin">Da mihi la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrymarum fontem, tum praecipuè, cùm preces &amp; ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones tibi offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro. Manualis cap. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note>. For the oliue tree is moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundant in fruite when it diſtilleth. And ſo a Chriſtian is moſt plentifull &amp; powre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in prayer when he weepeth. Hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on King Dauid ſaith, I am as a greene o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue tree, in the houſe of the Lord. And our Sauiour himſelfe whent often to the mount of Oliues, where hee offered vp prayers and ſupplications, with ſtrong
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:174760:17"/>crying and teares. And therefore he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs alſo, to haue fayth as a grayme of muſtard ſeede. Now muſtard ſeede hath his name in Greeke,<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> becauſe it makes the eyes weepe. So that hee which in prayer hath fayth, as a grayne of muſtard ſeede, hath ſuch a fayth, as makes his eyes weepe. And then Chriſt ſayes to him, Thou haſt wounded my heart with one of thine eyes. If with one, then much more with both. For, as Syneſius teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, weeping is more pearcing, and more forcible to perſwade God, and euen to wound his heart, then all the eloquence, then all the rhetorick in the world<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>. And Cpyrian ſayes, when the ſpirite of man ſendeth out ſighes in prayer, then the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God giues grace<note n="r" place="margin">Cum ſpiritus hominis ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, ſpiritus Dei aſpirat.</note>. And Ambroſe, God looketh when wee praye, that wee ſhould power out our teares, that hee might poure out his mercies<note n="ſ" place="margin">Expectat la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrymas no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtras, vt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundat pieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſuam. De paenit. l. c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note>. As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, Anna Samuels mother, in the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes of her ſoule wept ſore when ſhee prayed. Looke how ſalte vapours ariſe out of the ſea, which afterward are tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into a pleaſant ſhower: ſo out of the ſea of her ſorrowfull ſoule did ariſe ſobs and ſighes like ſalt vapours, which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:174760:17"/>were turned into aſweet ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of teares. Therefore God heard her prayer, and ſent her a ſonne. The rather, becauſe this weeping, the more bitter it was to her, the more ſweete it was to God. So Iacob wreſtled with God, and preuayled againſt God<note n="t" place="margin">Gen. 32.28.</note>. But the Prophet Oſee ſheweth, that his wreſtling was by weeping, and his preuailing was by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note n="u" place="margin">Oſe. c. 12. v. 4.</note>. So Ezechias being ſicke prayed, praying turn'd him toward the wall and wept<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And then with weeping as with gunſhot he battered downe that partiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wall of his ſinnes, which kept Gods louing countenance from him. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſayes the Lord to him, <hi>I haue heard thy prayers and thy teares.</hi> A ſtrange ſpeech. <hi>I haue heard thy prayers.</hi> That I vnderſtande well enough. But <hi>J haue heard thy teares.</hi> What ſhould bee the meaning of this, trow you? Haue teares tongues, I marueile, or can they ſpeake, that they may be heard? yea ſurely I dare bee bolde to ſay it. The cloud-cleauing thunder of th'almightie can not make ſuch a ratling ſound, and ſuch a roaring noyſe in the eares of man, as our teares doe in the eares of God. Therefore Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:174760:18"/>both before he had prayed,<note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 141.1.</note> deſireth God to heare the voice of his crying, and alſo after he had praied,<note n="y" place="margin">Pſal. 192.10.</note> thanketh God becauſe hee had heard the voice of his weeping. For indeede hee himſelfe alſo ſayes of himſelfe,<note n="(z)" place="margin">Pſal. 192.10.</note> I mingled my drink with weeping. And where was this drink of his, but in that cup of which he ſayes in an other place,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſal. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6.13</note> I will take the cup of ſaluation, (or of prayer, &amp; thankſgiuing) and call vpon the name of the Lord. So that Dauid mingling his drinke with weeping, mingled his prayer with wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping. Wherefore as Elizeus did caſt ſalt into the waters of Iericho, to make them ſweete: ſo muſt wee ſalt and ſeaſon our prayers with teares, to make them ſauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and delightſome to God. A man can neuer loue himſelfe aright, that doth not ſometimes weepe in <hi>repentance:</hi> nor his neighbour (if he be a preacher) that doth not ſometimes weepe in <hi>preaching:</hi> nor God, that doth not ſometimes weepe in <hi>prayer.</hi> So that we muſt not bee like the Stoikes which were neuer at all moued. Then we ſhal weepe too little. As is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in this ſecond part, BVT VVEEPE. VVEEP NOT FOR ME, BVT VVEEPE
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:174760:18"/>FOR YOVR SELVES.</p>
            <p>THe third part is next, VVEEPE NOT, BVT VVEEPE. Which noteth, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both the exceſſe and the want are to bee eſchewed, that therefore the true meane, which wee muſt keepe in wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, conſiſteth in an equall enterming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of theſe two extremities, VVEEPE NOT BVT VVEEPE both together. VVEEPE NOT, ſayes he, Too much is contrary to nature. BVT VVEEPE, too little is contrary to repentance. VVEEPE NOT, too much is contrary to reaſon. BVT VVEEPE, too little is contrarie to preaching. VVEEPE NOT, too much is contrarie to religion. BVT VVEEPE, too little is contrary to prayer. S. Paul char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth Timothie to be inſtant, in ſeaſon, &amp; out of ſeaſon. Firſt in ſeaſon, then out of ſeaſon. Teaching thereby that vnſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable opportunitie, is better then ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable importunity. Yet to keep a meane in exhorting, that wee muſt as well vſe importunitie ſometimes, ſo it bee in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as take an opportunitie alwaies, though it be out of ſeaſon. Euen ſo, ſayes our Sauiour here, VVEEPE NOT, BVT
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:174760:19"/>VVEEPE. Firſt weepe not, then but weep. Teaching thereby that not to weepe is better then to weep, yet to keep a meane in weeping, that we muſt, as well ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in not weeping weepe, as alwaies in weeping not weepe. For th'apoſtle ſaith, <hi>That they which reioyce muſt bee as though they reioyced not, and they which weepe muſt be as though they wept not. They which reioyce muſt bee as though they reioyced not,</hi> becauſe, ſayes Gregorie,<note n="b" place="margin">Gaudium huius vitae, vua acerba. In c. <hi>28.</hi> Iobi.</note> Al the ioye the godly haue in this life is as a ſower grape gathered out of time. And Ambroſe,<note n="c" place="margin">Non ſolum dolor, ſed et lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titia habet ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as lachrymas.</note> The children of God not onely in ſorrow, but euen in ioye alſo ſometimes ſhed teares. <hi>They reioyce as though they reioyced not. And they which weepe muſt be as though they wept not,</hi> becauſe, ſaies Macarius,<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Homil. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> Euen teares are a comforte to the righteous. And Ambroſe againe,<note n="c" place="margin">Eſt pijs affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tib quaedam c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>am flendi vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptas. De obi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu Valentiani. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>449.</hi>
               </note> To them that are well affected, weeping is a very great delight. <hi>They weepe as though they wept not.</hi> Wherefore as certaine leauen apples haue a ſowriſh ſweetnes, and ſome olde wines haue a ſweetiſh ſowrenes; ſo <hi>both our ſorrow muſt bee ioyfull, and our ioye muſt be ſorrowfull. Our ſorrow muſt bee ioyfull;</hi> as Chriſt did weepe vpon Palme
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:174760:19"/>ſunday. Chriſt did weepe. There is ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. Vpon Palme ſunday. There is ioy. <hi>And our ioy muſt be ſorowful;</hi> as the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites did eat the ſweet Eaſter lambe with ſower hearbs. The ſweete Eaſter lambe. There is ioy. VVEEPE NOT. With ſower hearbs. There is ſorow. BVT VVEEP. VVEEP NOT. This is a fiery ſpeech, as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> S. Iohn ſaies, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſts eies are as a flame of fire<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 19.12.</note>, that is, ſubiect now to no weeping. BVT VVEEPE. This is a watry ſpeech, as when Dauid ſaies, I water my couch with my teares. So that if we would reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cile theſe ſpeeches together, we muſt reconcile fire and water together. Gregory obſerueth, that in the raine-bow there are two co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, red which reſembleth fire, &amp; blew which reſembleth water<note n="(g)" place="margin">In arcu eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem color ignis &amp; aquae ſimul ostenditur: quia exparte eſt caeruleus, ex parte rubicun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus: vt vtriuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que iudicij te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis ſit, vnius videlicet faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endi, &amp; alteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us ſacti. Homil. <hi>8.</hi> in Ezec.</note>. Red, that we might not weepe, beholding the fire which ſhal burne whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt ſhall iudge the worlde: and blewe that wee might weepe, beholding the water which did flow when God did drowne the worlde. Therefore as there bee two colours, red and blew in one raine-bowe: So there muſt be two affections, ioye and ſorrowe in one heart. This the wiſedome of our aunceſtors ſeemeth to inſinuate, euen in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:174760:20"/>the apparell which they haue appointed to be worn at this ſolemnitie. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chief magiſtrates of the citie, this day weare ſcarlet gownes which is a kind of red like fire, but to morrowe they weare violet gownes which is a kind of blew like wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Wherefore the colours of the raine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow, which we ſee in your attire, doe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh you and vs all, that ioy and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row haue ſuch an entercourſe in this life, that though this day we VVEEPE NOT, yet to morrow perhaps we can not BVT VVEEPE. This day wee read Salomons ſongs, to morrow peraduenture we may read Ieremies lamentations. Now in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias his ſacrifice, there were not only the colours of fire and water, but euen fire and water indeede.<note n="h" place="margin">1. Reg. 18.38</note> In ſo much as the fire of the Lord conſumed &amp; licked the water of the aulter. And aſſuredly our ſorrowfull ſoule will be a moſt accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſacrifice to God, as Elias his ſacrifice was, if we haue both the fire of Aetna, &amp; the water of Nilus, ſo as the ardent fire of faith, well nie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume &amp; almoſt burn vp, the flowing ſtreame of loue.<note n="*" place="margin">In Epiro ſacer fons eſt frigidus vltra onmes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quas, &amp; ſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatae diuer ſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis. Nam ſi in eum ardentem demergas fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem, extinguit, ſi procul ac ſine igne admoueas ſuopte ingenio inflammat, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus. Poly. cap.</note> Auſtin re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth, that there is a fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine in Epirus, which not onely putteth out torches that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:174760:20"/>are lighted, but alſo lighteth torches that are put out<note n="i" place="margin">De ciuitate Dei lib <hi>25.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note>. Fulgoſus likewiſe repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth,<note n="k" place="margin">Mirum ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem dicere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bemus, apud Gratianopolin Gallicam vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ens. Nam quamuis cale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes aquas non hab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at, tamen ſimul cum ipſis aquis, flammas perſaepe emit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit. Fulgoſus lib. <hi>1.</hi> non longe à fine.</note> that there is an other fountaine neere Grenoble a citie in France, which although it haue not hotte waters as a bath, yet oftentimes together with bub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of water it caſteth vp flames of fire. The fountaine of teares that is in our eies muſt be like theſe two fountaines. As the Pſalmiſt witneſſeth, <hi>When my ſorow was ſtirred (ſayes he) my hart was hot with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in mee, and while I was muſing the fire kindled</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 30. v. 3.</note>.<hi>When my ſorrow was ſtirred.</hi> There is the firſt fountaine. <hi>My hart was hot within me.</hi> There is the torch ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. <hi>And while I was muſing.</hi> There is the other fountaine. <hi>The fire kindled.</hi> There is the flame burning. Whereupon one ſaies fitly, Our eies muſt neither bee drowned, nor drie<note n="m" place="margin">Nec fluant oculi, nec ſicci ſint. Seneca.</note>. If they wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fire, they will bee drowned. If they want water, they wilbe drie. Wherfore, both VVEEPE NOT, and BVT VVEEPE: both fire, and water, muſt goe together, that our eyes be neither drowned, nor drie. And this is the right moderatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we muſt keep in weeping, as appeareth in this third part, VVEEPE NOT, BVT VVEEPE
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:174760:21"/>both together. VVEEPE NOT FOR ME, BVT VVEEPE FOR YOVR SELVES.</p>
            <p>THe fourth part followeth, FOR ME. Weepe not too much for my death: For the death of Chriſt; is <hi>the death of death: the death of the diuell: the life of himſelfe: the life of man.</hi> The reaſon of all this, is his innocency and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which makes firſt that as the life of Chriſt is the life of life: ſo the death of Chriſt is <hi>the death of death.</hi> Put the caſe how you pleaſe, this is a moſt certaine trueth, that the gate of life had neuer bin opened vnto vs, if Chriſt who is <hi>the death of death</hi> had not by his death o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome death<note n="a" place="margin">Mors mortis morti mortem niſi morte de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſet, Caeleſtis vitae ianna clauſa foret.</note>. Therefore both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his death he threatneth and chalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth death ſaying,<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Oſe</hi> 13.14.</note> O death I will bee thy death: and alſo after his death he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rideth and ſcorneth death, ſaying,<note n="(c)" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.55.</note> O death thou art but a drone, where is now thy ſting<note n="(d)" place="margin">ſic Iohan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Piſtorius Eraſms Rote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodami affinis, igni creman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus dixit, O mors vbieſt tua victoria?</note>? Aske death any of you (I pray) and ſay, death how haſt thou loſt thy ſting? how haſt thou loſt thy ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth? What is the matter that virgins and very children do now contemne thee, wheras kinges and euen tyrants did before feare
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:174760:21"/>thee? Death (I warrant) wil anſwere you, that the only cauſe of this is the death of Chriſt. Euen as a bee ſtinging a dead body takes no hurt, but ſtinging a liue body many times loſeth both ſting &amp; life together; in like maner death, ſo long as it ſtung mortal men only which were dead in ſin was neuer a whit the worſe, but when it ſtunge Chriſt once, who is life it ſelfe, by and by it loſt both ſtinge and ſtrength. Therefore as the braſen ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent was ſo farre from hurting the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites that contratiwiſe it healed them: after the ſame ſort death is now ſo far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hutting any true Iſraelite, that on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, if affliction as a fiery ſerpent ſting vs, or if any thing els hurt vs, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently it is helped &amp; redreſſed by death. Thoſe which will needs play the hob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goblins or the nightewalkinge ſpirites (as we call them) al the while they ſpeak vnder a hollow vault, or leape forth with an vgly vizard vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their faces, they are ſo terrible that he which thinkes himſelfe noſmall man may perhaps be affrighted with them. But if ſome luſty fellowe chaunce to ſteppe into one of theſe and cudgle him well fauoredly, and pull the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:174760:22"/>vizarde from his face, then euery boye laughes him to ſcorne. So is it in this matter. Death was a terrible bulbegger, and made euery man afraide of him a great while, but Chriſt dying buckled with this bulbegger, and coniured him (as I may ſay) out of his hollowe vault, when as the dead comminge out of the graues were ſeene in leruſalem: and puld the vizard from his face, when as he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe riſinge, left the linne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> clothes which were the vizard of death behinde him. Therefore as that aſſe called <hi>Cumanus aſinus</hi> ietting vp and downe in a lyons skinne did for a time terrifie his maiſter, but afterwards being diſcried did bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit him very much: ſemblably death ſtands nowe like a ſilly aſſe, hauing his lyons skinne puld ouer his eares, and is ſo farre from terrifying any, that it bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits all true chriſtians, becauſe by it they reſt from their laboures, and if they bee oppreſſed with troubles or cares, when they come to death they are diſcharged; death as an aſſe doth beare theſe burdens for them. Obleſſed, bleſſed be our lord, which hath ſo diſarmed death that it can not doe vs any hurt, no more then a bee
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:174760:22"/>can which hath no ſting; nay rather it doth vs much good, as the braſen ſerpent did the Iſraelites: which hath ſo diſmaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked death that it can not make vs afraid, no more then a ſcarbug can which hath novizard, nay rather as an aſſe beareth his maſters burdens, ſo death eaſeth and refreſheth vs. This hath Chriſt done by his death. Hee that felleth a tree vpon which the ſun ſhineth, may well cut the tree, but can not hurt the ſunne He that poweeth water vpon yron which is red botte, may well quench the heate, but he cannot hurt the yron. And ſo Chriſt the ſunne of righteouſnes did driue away the ſhadowe of death: and as glowinge yon was too hot and too hard a morſell for death to digeſt. All the while Adam did eate any other fruit which God gaue him leaue to eate, he was nouriſhed by it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but when he had taſted of the forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den tree he periſhed. Right ſo death had free leaue to deuoure any other man, Chriſt only excepted, but when it went about to deſtroy Chriſt, then it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed it ſelfe. Thoſe barbarous people called Cannibals which feed only vpon rawe fleſh, eſpecially of men, if they hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:174760:23"/>to eate a peece of roſted meate, commonly they ſurſet of it and die E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo the right Canniball the only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourer of all mankinde, death I meane, taſting of Chriſtes fleſhe, and finding it not to bee rawe (ſuch as it was vſed to eate) but wholſome and heauenly meat indeede, preſently tooke a ſurfet of it, &amp; within three dayes dyed. For euen as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iudas had receiued a ſop at Chriſts hand, anon after his bowels guſhed out: in like ſort death beinge ſo ſaucie as to ſnatch a ſop (as it were) of Chriſtes fleſh, and a little bit of his body, was by &amp; by like Iudas choked and ſtrangled with it, and faine to yeeld it vp againe, when Chriſt on Eaſter day reuiued. Death I wiſſe, had not bin brought vp ſo dainti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before, nor vſed to ſuch manner of meat, but alwaies had rauened either with Mithridates daughters vpon the poiſon of ſinne, or elſe with Noahs crow vpon the carrion of corruption. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore nowe ſaies Fulgentius,<note n="e" place="margin">Mors Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum guſtauit, ſed non deglu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuit.</note> death did indeede taſte of Chriſte, but could not ſwallow him vp, nor digeſt him. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe Chriſt as ſoone as euer he had but a little taſted of death<note n="f" place="margin">Hebr. cap. <hi>2.</hi> ver. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> eftſones hee
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:174760:23"/>did deuoure death, he did ſwallowe vp death in victory. And ſo the death of Chriſt by reaſon of his righteouſnes is <hi>the death of death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is alſo the <hi>death of the diuell.</hi> As the Apoſtle ſaies that by his death he did ouercome not only death, but him alſo which had the power of death, the diuel. It is reported that the Libard vſeth a ſhaunge kinde of pollicy to kill the ape. Hee lyeth downe vpon the grounde as though he were ſtarke dead: which the apes ſeeing come all together, &amp; in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight skip vp vpon him. This the Libard beareth patiently till he thinks they haue wearied themſelues with their ſporting. Then ſodainly hee likewiſe leaps vp and catches one in his mouth, and in each foote one, which immediatly he killeth &amp; deuoureth<note n="(g)" place="margin">Concul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant inſultantes lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibrij cauſae donec pardalis ſentiens illas iam ſaltando defatigatas de repente reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſcens aliam dentib. aliam vnguib. corri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit. Eraſ. Prou. Pardi mortem adſimulat.</note>. This was Chriſts polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. He was layd in the duſt for dead. The diuel then inſulted ouer him and tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled vpon him. But he like a liuely Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard ſtartinge vp on Eaſter day aſtoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth the ſouldiers ſet to keep him which were the diuels apes, &amp; made them lye like dead men<note n="h" place="margin">Math. cap. <hi>28.</hi> ver. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note>. Euen as he tolde them before by his prophet, ſaying. I will be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:174760:24"/>to them as a very Lyon, and as a Lybard in the way of Aſhur<note n="i" place="margin">Oſe. cap. <hi>13.</hi> ver. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note>. For as blind Samſon by his death killed the Philiſtins, when they were playinge the apes in mocking and mowinge at him<note n="(k)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudicum</hi> 10. <hi>ver.</hi> 25.</note>: ſo Chriſt by his death deſtroied the diuell. Scaliger writeth that the Chameleon when hee eſpies a ſerpent taking ſhade vnder a tree, climes vp into that tree and lets downe a threed, breathed out of his mouth as ſmall as a ſpiders threed, at the end wherof there is a little drop as cleare as any pearle, which fallinge vpon the ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts head kils him<note n="(l)" place="margin">Ex ore filum demittit ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neorum more: in cuius fili ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremo guttula eſt margarttae ſplendore, ea tactus in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice ſerpens moritur. Ex. <hi>190.</hi>
               </note>. Chriſt is this Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meleon. He climes vp into the tree of his croſſe and lets downe a threed of bloud, iſſuing out of his ſide, like Rahabs red threed hanging out of her window<note n="(m)" place="margin">Signa fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vexilla dominicae paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionis attollens coccum in fene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra ligauit. Ambro. de fide libro <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi> &amp; Paulinus Natali. <hi>8.</hi> Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niceo proprium ſignauit velle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re tectum.</note>, the leaſt drop wherof beeing ſo precious and ſo peereles falling vpon the ſerpents head kils him. The wilde bull of al things can not abide any red coloure. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the hunter for the nonce ſtandinge before a tree, puts on a redde garment. Whom when the bull ſees, he runnes at him as hard as he can driue. But the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſlipping a ſide the buls hornes ſticke faſt in the tree. As when Dauid ſlipped
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:174760:24"/>aſide Sauls ſpeare ſtuck faſt in the wall<note n="(n)" place="margin">1. Sam. 19.10.</note> Such a hunter is Chriſt. Chriſt ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding before the tree of his croſſe, puts on a red garment dipt and died in his owne bloud, as one that commeth with redde garments from Bozra<note n="(o)" place="margin">Eſa. cap. 63.1.</note>. Therfore the diuell and his angels like wilde bulles of Bazan<note n="(p)" place="margin">Pſalm. 22.12.</note> ran at him. But he ſhifting for himſelfe, their hornes ſticke faſt in his croſſe. As Abrahams ram by his hornes ſtuck faſt in the briers<note n="(q)" place="margin">Geneſis. 22.13.</note>. Thus is the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell caught and killed. A Dragon indeed kils an Elephant: yet ſo as the Elephant falling downe kils the dragon hith him. An Elephant kils Elezar: yet ſo as Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>azar falling down kils the Elepha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with him<note n="r" place="margin">1. Mach. 6.46.</note>. And accordingly to this, the diuel killing Chriſt was killed by Chriſt. Yea as an Elephant is ſtronger then the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, and Eleazar is ſtronger then the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lephant: ſo Chriſt is ſtronger then them both. For the Elephant doth not liue af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hee hath killed the Dragon, neither doth Eleazar liue after he hath killed the Elephant: but Chriſt liueth after he hath deſtroyed the diuell. Leauing the diuell dead, he is nowe riſen himſelfe from the dead. Wherfore as a Lybard killeth the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:174760:25"/>ape: and a Chameleon the ſerpent: and a hunter the bull: and an Elephant the dragon: &amp; Eleazar the Elepha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t himſelfe: ſo Chriſt the true Eleazar, which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies the helpe of God, hath by his death killed, that miſcheeuous ape the diuell: that olde ſerpent the diuell: that wilde bull the deuill: that great dragon the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill: that raginge elephant the deuill. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Mahomet, the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of that name, beſeeged Belgrade in Seruia, one of his captaines at length got vp vpon the wall of the city with banner diſplayed. A no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Bohemian eſpying this ranne to the captaine, &amp; claſping him faſt about the middle, asked one Capiſtranus ſtanding beneath, whether it would be any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his ſoule, if he ſhould caſt himſelfe downe headlong with that dogge (ſo he tearmed the turke,) to bee ſlaine with him? Capiſtranus anſwering that it was no daunger at all to his ſoule, the Bohemian foorthwith tumbled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe downe with the Turke in his armes, and ſo by his owne death only ſaued the life of all the city<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">Zieglerus. de illuſtribus viris <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tae cap. <hi>98.</hi>
               </note>. Such an exploit was this of Chriſt. The diuell like the great Turke beſieging not only one city, but
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:174760:25"/>euen all mankinde, Chriſt alone like this noble Bohemian encountred with him. And ſeeing the caſe was ſo, that this dog the diuel, could not be killed ſtarke dead except Chriſt died alſo; therfore he made no reckoninge of his life, but gaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to death for vs, that hee only dying for all the people, by his death our deadly enemy might for euer be deſtroyed. For ſo Origen teſtifieth that there were two crucified vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe of Chriſt. Chriſt himſelfe, viſibly: with his will: and for a time. The diuell, inuiſibly: againſt his will: and for euer<note n="(r)" place="margin">Homi. <hi>8.</hi> in Ioſua.</note>. Therfore the croſſe is that victorious chariot in the vpper part wherof Chriſt ſitteth as a triumpha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t conqueror, and in the lower part of it the diuell is drawen as a captiue, and is made an open ſpectacle of ignominy &amp; reproch. Diuerſe auncient fathers note the virgin Mary was maried that the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell might be deceiued. For he knewe well enough Chriſt ſhould be borne of a virgin. But he neuer ſuſpected bleſſed Mary was a virgin, conſidering ſhe was wedded to Ioſeph. Therfore he did not lye in wait to deſtroy the ſeed of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſo circumſpectly as otherwiſe hee
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:174760:26"/>would if he had bin aware or wiſt any ſuch thing. So that the birth of Chriſt did coſen the diuel. But the death of Chriſt did conquer the diuell. And that much more gloriouſly when the temple of his body was vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the pinnacle of the croſſe, then when the body of his croſſe was vpon the pinnacle of the temple. For when he was vpon the temple his breath ſpake better thinges then Sathan: but when he was vpon the croſſe his bloud ſpake better things then Abell: and there his breath came from his lunges out of his mouth, but here his bloud came from his heart out of his ſide: and there hee fought ſtanding ſtoutly to it, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Sathan hee would not in any wiſe throwe down himſelfe, but here he skirmiſhed yeelding and humbling him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the death of the croſſe: and there the diuill aſcended vp to him vnto the toppe of an high mountaine, and ſo (as I may ſay) bad him baſe at his own goale, but here he himſelfe deſcended down to the diuell into the neathermoſt hell, and ſo ſpoiled principalities and powers, and ſlewe the great Leuiathan in the very bottome of his own bottomles pit. For
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:174760:26"/>the diuell like a greedy rauenous fiſhe ſnatching at the baite of Chriſts body (as Damaſcene ſpeaketh) was pearced through and twicht vp with the hooke of his Deity<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>. Therefore both before Chriſtes paſſion, Peter tooke mony out of a fiſhes mouth to pay his tribute: and alſo after Chriſtes paſſion, the diſciples broyled a fiſhe for him to feede vpon. Whereby we ſee, that Chriſt, who made a fiſhe pay tribute to Caeſar for him, made the diuell alſo pay tribute to death for him: and on the other ſide that the diuell while he went about to catch this good fiſhe, which is Ieſus Chriſt Gods ſonne the ſauiour (as Methodius and Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>billa proue the letters of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note n="(x)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſignifie) was himſelfe caught, yea alſo killed by Chriſt. So that all the while Chriſt was buried in the graue, the diuel was broyled in hell. Wherefore as it was booteles for Golias to brandiſhe his ſpeare againſt Dauid: ſo it little auailed the diuell to ſhake his ſpeare likewiſe in the hand of the ſouldier againſt the heart of Chriſt. For as Dauid hauinge heard Golias prate &amp; talke his pleaſure, when they came to the poynt at the firſt ſtroke
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:174760:27"/>ouerthrew him: ſo Chriſt with that very ſelfe ſame ſpeare which gaue him a little venny in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon, or (if it be lawful for me ſo to ſpeake) but a phillip on the ſide, which was ſoone after recured, gaue the diuell a deadly wound in the forehead, which with all his pawes hee ſhall neuer be able to claw off. And again, as Dauid onely with his ſling wrought this feate: ſo Chriſt onely by his death, and by the power of his croſſe, which is the ſling of Dauid<note n="(y)" place="margin">Sanè crux ipſa funda est, qua Dauid Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liath horren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum armis &amp; formidabilem viſu proſtrauit hunet. Cyr. Ioh. l. <hi>8.17.</hi>
               </note> did conquer &amp; ſubdue the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil. And ſo the death of Chriſt by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his righteouſnes is <hi>the death of the deuil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is on the other ſide <hi>the life of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</hi> That which was prophecied in the Pſalme is here fulfilled in chriſt.<note n="z" place="margin">Pſal. 92.12.</note> The iuſt ſhal flouriſh as the palme tree. In the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew it is <hi>Tamar,</hi> which ſignifies only a palme tree. But in the greek it is <hi>Phoinix</hi> which ſignifies not only a palme tree, but alſo a Phenix. Which tranſlation proueth two thinges. Firſt, that Ieſus the iuſt one did moſt floriſh when he was moſt affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. For the iuſt ſhall flouriſh as the palme tree<note n="a" place="margin">Chattamar.</note>. Now the palme tree, though it haue many waights at the top, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſnakes at the roote, yet ſtill it ſaies, I
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:174760:27"/>am neither oppreſſed with the waights, nor diſtreſſed with the ſnakes<note n="b" place="margin">Nec premor, nec perimor.</note>. And ſo Chriſt the true palme tree, though all the iudgements of God, and all the ſinnes of the worlde, like vnſupportable waightes were laide vpon him, yea though the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Iewes ſtoode beneath like venemous ſnakes hiſſing and byting at him, yet he was, neither ſo oppreſſed with them, nor ſo diſtreſſed with theſe, but that euen vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his croſſe he did moſt floriſh, when he was moſt afflicted. As peny royall being hung vp in the larder houſe, yet buds his yellow flower: and Noahs oliue tree be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing drownde vnder the water, yet keepes his greene braunch: and Aarons rod be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing clunge and drie, yet brings forth ripe almonds: and Moſes bramble buſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſet on fire, yet ſhines and is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed. Secondly, that Ieſus the iuſt one did moſt liue, when hee ſeem'de moſt to be dead. For the iuſt ſhall flouriſh as the phenix<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>. Now the phenix though ſitting in his neſt among the holy ſpices of Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia he be burnt to aſhes, yet ſtill he ſayes, I die not but olde age dieth in me<note n="c" place="margin">Moritur me non moriente ſenectus.</note>. And ſo Chriſt the true phenix, though lying in his graue among the hot ſpices wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:174760:28"/>with Nichodemus embalmde him, hee was neuer like to riſe from death to life a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, yet he dyed not but mortalitie di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in him, and immortalitie ſo liued in him, that euen in his ſepulchre hee did moſt liue, when hee ſeemde moſt to bee dead. As the Laurell is greeneſt in the fouleſt winter: and the lime is hotteſt in the coldeſt water: and the glow-worme ſhineth brighteſt when the night is dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt: and the ſwan ſingeth ſweeteſt whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his death is neereſt<note n="(d)" place="margin">Cantator cygnus funeris ipſe ſui. Mart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> alis lib. <hi>13.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pigr.</note>. Epaminondas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſore wounded in fight, demaunded of his ſouldiers ſtanding by, whether his enemies were ouerthrowne or no? They anſwered yea. Then whether his buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler were whole or no? They anſwered al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo I. Nay then (ſayes he) all is well. This is not the ende of my life, but the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of my glory. For now your deere Epaminondas dying thus gloriouſly ſhal rather be borne agayne then buried<note n="(e)" place="margin">Nunc enim veſter Epami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nondas naſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quia ſic moritur.</note> Chriſt likewiſe was ſore wounded. But his enemies death and the deuill were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowne and ſpoyled. His buckler, which was his Godhead, was whole and vntouched. Therfore there was no harme done. His death was no death, but an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:174760:28"/>vnto greater glory<note n="(f)" place="margin">Ego ſi exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatus ſuero. Ioh. <hi>12.32.</hi>
               </note>. That no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Eunuch riding in his cooch read in Eſay, that Chriſt was ſilent before his death, as a lambe before the ſhearer. He ſayes not, before the butcher, but, before the ſhearer. Inſinuating that death did not kill Chriſt, but onely ſheare him a little. Neither yet had death Chriſtes fleece when hee was ſhorne. For Chriſt taking to himſelfe a ſpoungefull of vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar<note n="g" place="margin">Ioh. ca. 19.29</note>, that is, ful of our ſharpe and ſower ſinnes, did giue vs for it purple wool full of bloud,<note n="h" place="margin">Heb. c. 9.19.</note> that is, full of his pure and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect iuſtice. And indeed the onely liuery which Chriſt our Lorde and maſter gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth all vs that are his faithfull ſeruants, is a coate made of this purple wooll. The Pſal miſt ſayes, that God giueth his ſnow like wooll. But here wee may turne the ſentence, and ſay, that Chriſt giueth his wooll like ſnow. For as ſnow couereth the ground when it is ragged and defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: ſo Chriſts wooll which is his coate without ſeame, couereth our ſinnes, and though they were as crimſon, yet maketh them white as ſnow. And as Gedeons fleece when it was moiſt, the earth was drie, but when it was drie the earth was
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:174760:29"/>moiſt: So when Chriſts fleece was moiſt as a greene tree, then were all wee drie like rotten ſtickes, but when his fleece was drie, all the bloud and water being wrung out of his precious ſide, then were we moiſt'ned with his grace. Wherefore ſeeing death had not Chriſtes fleece whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was ſhorne, but we haue it which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in him, it followeth that neither death was the better nor chriſt the worſe. But as a lamb is much more nimble and liuely for ſhearing: ſo this ſhearing of death was a kinde of quickening to the lambe of God, and onely a trimming to him before he aſcended to his father, as Ioſeph was trim'd and poul'd before hee appeared to Pharaoh. For looke how A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam ſlept: ſo Chriſt died<note n="i" place="margin">Dormit A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, moritur Christus. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper.</note>. When Adam ſlept, his ſide was opened: when Chriſt died, his ſide was opened. Adams ſide being opened, fleſh and bone were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out: Chriſts ſide being opened, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and bloud were taken out. Of Adams fleſh and bone the woman was built: of Chriſtes water and bloud the Church is built. So that the death of Chriſt is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but the ſleepe of Adam. For as he ſayes of the damſels death, The dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:174760:29"/>is not dead but ſleepeth; ſo hee ſayes of his owne death, I laid me downe and ſlept, and roſe vp againe for the Lord ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained me. And in an other place, when God the father ſayth to his ſonne, Awake my glory, awake my lute and harpe: God the ſonne anſweres to his father, I will awake right early. That veſſel which Peter ſawe in a traunce, which came down from heauen to the earth, and was knit at the foure corners, and had all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of beaſtes in it, did betoken Chriſt. Chriſt came downe from heauen to the earth: and his ſtorie is knit vp by the foure Euangeliſtes: and hee hath made Iewes and Gentiles, yea all nations, though they were as bad as beaſtes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, yet he hath made them all, I ſay, one in himſelfe. Nowe ſaies Caſſianus, it is worth the noting, that the holy Ghoſt ſaies not, this veſſel was a ſheete, but was like a ſheete<note n="k" place="margin">Pulchrè ait, Non linteum ſed, Quaſi lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teum.</note>. A ſheete may ſignifie ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſleep or death. Becauſe there is both a ſleeping ſheete, and a winding ſheete. But neither was Peters veſſell a ſleepe, though it were like a ſheete: neither was Chriſts bodie dead, though it were lapt in a ſheete. For we our ſelues canne not
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:174760:30"/>ſo properly bee ſaide to liue in our firſt birth, as in our ſecond birth: and Chriſts life when hee lay in that new wombe, in which neuer any other was conceiued, is nothing to his life, when hee laye in that newe tombe, in which neuer any other was buried. Wherefore as Iacob trauai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling towards Haram, when he had layde an heape of ſtones vnder his head, and taken a nap by the way, was much reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with it after his tedious iourney: ſo Chriſt trauailing towardes heauen, when he had ſlept a little in that ſtony ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre which was hewen out of a rock, liued then moſt princely after his painfull paſſion. Tell me when did Ionas liue? in the hatches of the ſhip, or in the bellie of the whale? In the hatches of the ſhippe? why? I am ſure you will not ſay ſo. That was nothing. But to liue in the bellie of the whale when the marriners were in extreme ieopardie and daunger vpon the water, and yet Ionas moſt ſafe and ſecure vnder the water, this indeede was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what. Who euer ſaw ſuch a wonder? The waues were one while hoiſted vp to the higheſt clowdes, an other while hurled downe to the nethermoſt depth, Ionas
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:174760:30"/>ſelfe being all this while in the very gulfe of deſtruction, and yet not one haire the worſe. Chriſts caſe was the ſame. As Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas was in the bellie of the whale three daies and three nightes: ſo and ſo long was the ſonne of man in the bowels of the earth. Yet he had no more hurt then Ionas had. But liued better vnder the earth then we can vpon the earth, better in death then we can in life. Tell me whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did Daniell liue? In the kings court? or in the lyons denne? In the kinges court? why? there is no great reaſon for that. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man might haue liued there. But to liue in the lions den, when the mouth of the den was ſhut, and the mouths of the lyons open, this indeed was the life of an angel &amp; no man. What king could euer make lyons attend, and waite vpon him? Yet here you might haue ſeene worthie Daniel ſitting in the midſt of many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry lyons, when as the lions lay downe at his feete couching and crouching be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and adored their owne pray caſt vnto them, which otherwiſe they would haue werried, and being beaſtes became men in humanitie towarde this ſaint, ſeeing men became beaſtes in cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:174760:31"/>againſt him. The ſame reaſon was in Chriſt. His ſepulchre was ſealed as wel as Daniels den. And hee ſaies alſo of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the Pſalme, My ſoule is among lyons. Theſe lyons were the terrours of death, and the horrours of hell. Yet hee tooke no more hurt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Daniel did. But brake the chaines of death into fitters, and the gates of hell into ſhiuers, and then moſt gloriouſly triumphed. And ſo the death of Chriſt by reaſon of his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes is <hi>the life of himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is laſtly <hi>the life of man.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſts ſpeare had opened that way of life which the Cherubins ſword had ſtopt vp, then ſaies our Sauiour to the theefe, This day ſhalt thou be with me in para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice. Adam and Eue both in one day were expelled out of paradice. Chriſt &amp; the theefe both in one day were receiued into paradice. Yea both in one houre of the day. For about noone when the winde blewe Adam and Eue were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled. And ſo about the ſixt houre, that is about twelue a clocke in the day time, Chriſt and the theefe were receiued. Chriſt ſaying to the theefe while he did draw him vp into paradice<note n="l" place="margin">Oſe cap. 11.</note> I do draw
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:174760:31"/>thee with the cordes of a man euen with bands of loue. But the ſeptuaginte tranſlate the hebrewe words<note n="m" place="margin">Bechauele adam.</note> which ſignifie, with the cordes of a man, into thoſe greeke words<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> which ſignifie with the deſtruction of a man. As if Chriſt ſhould ſay thus to the theefe. I do ſo dearely loue thee that I am content, my ſelfe to bee deſtroied that thou mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt bee ſaued, my ſelfe to dye that thou maieſt liue. I doe drawe thee with the deſtruction of a man, euen with bandes of loue. So that the theefe who ſawe his owne woundes and death in Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, did ſee alſo Chriſtes ſauing health &amp; life in his owne body. As Alcuinus ſayes writing vpon the ſixt of Iohn<note n="o" place="margin">Aſſumpſit vita mortem, vt mors accipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret vitam,</note>; when the liuinge Lord dyed, then the dyinge theefe liued. Notably ſayes the prophet<note n="p" place="margin">Lamen. 4. ver. 21.</note>, The breath of our noſtrels, Chriſt the Lord is taken in our ſins, to whom wee ſayd wee ſhall liue in thy ſhadowe. If Chriſt be the breath of our noſtrels, then he is our life. And againe, if we liue in his ſhadowe, then we liue in his death. For where there is breath in a ſhadowe, there there is life in death. Nowe as the ouerſhadowing of the holy Ghoſt was
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:174760:32"/>the life of Chriſt; ſo the ouerſhadowing of Chriſte, is the life of man. And as Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſhadowe gaue health to the ſicke: ſo Chriſtes ſhadowe giueth life to the dead. yea a thouſand times rather Chriſts then Peters. For as Elias his ſpirit was doubled vpon Elizeus, becauſe Elias be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aliue reſtored ſome to life, but Elize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, as Ierom ſayes, being dead raiſed vp one from the dead<note n="q" place="margin">Mortuus mortuum ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citauit.</note> ſo Peters ſpirit was doubled vpon Chriſt, becauſe Peter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aliue was a phiſition to the liuinge, but Chriſt as Chryſoſtome ſaith, beinge dead was a phiſition to the dead<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Or rather indeed in this compariſon there is no compariſon. But as Peters ſpirit was a ſhadowe to Chriſts ſpirit: ſo Peters ſhadowe was nothing to Chriſts death. Ezechias ſeeing the ſhadow of the ſunne goe ten degrees backe in the diall, was aſſured by this ſigne, that he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer of his ſicknes<note n="f" place="margin">Eſay. cap. 38.8.</note> Sick Ezechias may ſignifie all mankinde which is ſicke by reaſon of ſinne. But this is an vnfallible ſigne we ſhall recouer, becauſe the ſun hath gone ten degrees backe in the dyal. The ſun of righteouſnes Ieſus Chriſt hath for our ſake made him-ſelfe lower by
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:174760:32"/>many degrees in the earth. My father is greater then I. There hee is gone backe tenne degrees belowe his father. Thou haſt made him lower then the angels. There hee is gone backe ten degrees be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe the angels. I am a worme and no man. There he is gone back ten degrees belowe men. A liue dogge is better then a dead lyon<note n="(t)" place="margin">Eccleſ. <hi>9.</hi> ver. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> There he is gone backe ten degrees below wormes. For he was not counted ſo good as a liue worme, but was buried in the earth as a dead ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be meate for the wormes, if it had bin poſſible for this holy one to ſee cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. But bleſſed, O bleſſed bee our Lord! Chriſt beeinge in the forme of God was buried in the graue, &amp; ſo was made lower then his father; nay lower then angels; nay lower then men; nay lower then wormes: that we being now no better then wormes might be crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in heauen, and ſo might bee made higher then wormes; yea higher then men; yea higher then angels; yea parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the ſame life and kingdome with Chriſt. Pliny reporteth<note n="u" place="margin">L. <hi>36.</hi> cap. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> that there was a diall ſet in Campus martius to note the ſhadowes of the ſun which agreeing
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:174760:33"/>very well at the firſt, afterwards for thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty yeers together did not agree with the ſun. All the time of thoſe thirty yea three and thirty yeeres that Chriſt liued in his humiliation here vpon earth, you might haue ſeene ſuch a diall. In which time the ſhadowe of the diall did not agree with the ſhining of the ſun. But thankes be to God, all the better for vs. When the ſunne went backward ten degrees in the diall, then Ezechias went forward fifteen degrees in his life. He liued fifteene yeers longer. And ſo the going of this ſunne Ieſus Chriſt ten degrees backward, hath healed all our ſicknes, and ſet vs a thow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand degrees forward, and infinitely ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced vs by his death to euerlaſtinge life. For Chriſt is that louinge Rachell, which dyes her ſelfe in childbirth to bringe forth her ſonne Beniamin aliue; Chriſt is that righteous Adam which by the bloudy ſweat of his browes hath earned for vs the bread of life; Chriſt is that iuſt Noah, which ſhutting vp him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in his Arcke as in a ſepulchre ſaueth all that come to him aliue: Chriſt is that tender Pellican which woundinge his own breſt, doth with his bloud reſtore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:174760:33"/>his yong ones to life. And euen as when many birds are caught in a net, if a Pellican, or any other great bird that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge them get out, all the reſt that are little ones follow after: ſemblably Chriſt as a great bird hauing broken through the net of death, all we eſcape with him: So that wee may ſay with the Pſalmiſt, Our ſoule is eſcaped as a bird out of the ſnare of the fouler, the ſnare is broken &amp; we are deliuered. Arnobius vpon theſe wordes in the pſalme<note n="x" place="margin">Pſalm. <hi>138.8.</hi>
               </note>, Deſpiſe not the worke of thine own hands, writeth thus, We are the worke of thine own handes, ſeeing wee are thy workmanſhippe<note n="(y)" place="margin">Eph. <hi>2.10.</hi> lyſius ſumus factura conditi in Chriſto. Quantum ad ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiam fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tum ad gratiam condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. Tertull. aduer. Mar. l. <hi>5.</hi> non longe a fine.</note>. Now becauſe the worke of thy handes was deſtroied by the worke of our hands, therfore were thy handes nayled to the croſſe for our ſinnes. That thoſe handes of thine might repaire againe the worke of thy handes by the tree of the croſſe, which was deſtroyed by the tree of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence. Thus far Arnobius. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee may gather that the fruit of the tree of knowledge of good and euill is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, that is death, but the fruit of the tree of life, that is of the croſſe of Chriſt, is life. When Alexander had throwen downe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:174760:34"/>the walles of the Thebes, Phryne a har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot promiſed that ſhe would at her own charges repaire them againe, ſo that the citizens would ſuffer this title to bee gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vpon the gate, <hi>Alexander hath throwen them downe, but Phryne hath raiſed them vp</hi>
               <note n="(z)" place="margin">A <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Plutar.</note>. The caſe is quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary here. Eue hath ouerthrowene not only Thebes, but euen all mankinde. Chriſt hath at his owne coſt and charges repaired and built vs vp againe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee muſt graue this title vpon the croſſe of Chriſt, <hi>Eue hath throwne vs downe, But Chriſt hath raiſed vs vp.</hi> Eues tree of knowledge of good and euill hath throwen vs downe, but Chriſts tree of life hath raiſed vs vp. Nay I will be bold to ſay yet more. What is that? Marry this, That as far as the tree of life excelleth the tree of knowledge of good and euill, ſo farre the croſſe of Chriſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celleth the tree of life. I know well many will muſe &amp; maruel much what I meane to ſay ſo. And ſome perhaps will ſcarce beleeue it is true which I ſay. Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, moſt chriſtian and bleſſed brethren, make you no doubt of it. For it is not my opinion or my ſpeech only. They are the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:174760:34"/>very words of our ſauiour. I came, ſaies he, that men might haue life<note n="(a)" place="margin">Iohn chap. 10.10.</note>, &amp; that they might haue it more aboundantly. More aboundantly? What is that? That aboundantly wee might haue more life by the croſſe of Chriſt, then euer wee could haue had by the tree of life: that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly we might gaine more by the obedience of Chriſt in his death, then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer wee loſt or could loſe by the diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of Adam in his life. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though that ſinne of Adam was ſo haynous and ſo horrible; that it caſt the image of God out of Paradiſe; that it polluted all the race of mankind; that it condemned the whole world; that it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced the very frame of heauen it ſelfe; yet conſidering the ſequele, how not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the guilt of this ſinne, but euen the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry memory of it is nowe vtterly aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by the bloud of Chriſt, S. Gregory is not afraid to ſay, O happy, happy, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py man was Adam that euer hee ſo ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and tranſgreſſed againſt God<note n="b" place="margin">O foelix culpa quae talem ac tantum meru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it habere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demptorem.</note>. Becauſe by this meanes both hee and all wee haue found; ſuch plentifull redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſuch vneſtimable mercy; ſuch ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perabundant grace; ſuch ſelicity; ſuch e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:174760:35"/>ſuch life by Chriſts death. For as hony beeinge found in a dead lyon, the death of the lyon was the ſuſtenance of Sampſon; ſo Chriſts gall is our hony<note n="c" place="margin">Chriſtifel noſtrum mel.</note>, &amp; the bitter death of Chriſt by reaſon of his righteouſnes is <hi>the</hi> ſweet <hi>life of man.</hi> Thus you ſee that the death of Chriſt is, <hi>the death of death; the death of the diuel; the life of himſelfe; the life of man.</hi> And therefore he ſaies in this fourth part, weep not too much for my death, FOR MEE. VVEEP NOT FOR MEE BVT VVEEP FOR YOVR SELVES.</p>
            <p>I Perceiue beloued I haue bin ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what long in this part. Therefore I will make more haſt in the reſt, and do what I can deuiſe that I may not ſeeme tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous vnto you. Now then to the fift part. FOR YOVR SELVES. Weepe not too little for your owne life. For the life of man is quite contrary. The life of man is <hi>the life of death: the life of the diuell: the death of himſelfe: the death of Chriſt.</hi> The reaſon of all this is his iniquity and ſinne. Which euen in gods deare chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſaies Barnard, is caſt downe, but not caſt out<note n="d" place="margin">Deiectum, non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ectum.</note>. Therfore though ſin can
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:174760:35"/>not ſometimes rule ouer vs, becauſe it is caſt downe, yet it will alwaies dwell in vs, becauſe it is not caſt out. For it is ſo bred in the bone, that till our bones bee with Ioſephs bones caried out of Aegypt, that is out of the world, ſin can not bee carried out of our bones. The iriſh hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry telleth vs that the city of Waterford giueth this poſey <hi>Intacta manet</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">It continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vntouched.</note>. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſince it was firſt conquered by king Henry the ſecond, it was neuer yet attaynted, no not ſo much as touched with treaſon. Alſo that the yle of Arren in that country hath ſuch a pure ayre, that it was neuer yet infected with the plague. Wee can not ſay thus of the nature of man, That either it is ſo cleere from trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as that city is, or els that it is ſo cleare from infection, as that Iland is. Nay our very reaſon is treaſon, and our beſt affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is no better then an infection, if it be well ſifted in the ſight of God. Eua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grius recordeth<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>libr.</hi> 5. <hi>ca.</hi> 15.</note>, that the Romanes got ſuch a victory ouer Choſroes, one of the Perſian kings, that this Choſroes made a lawe, that neuer after any king of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia ſhould moue warre againſt the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes. We cannot poſſibly ſubdue ſin
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:174760:36"/>in ſuch ſort, as the Romanes did this Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian king. But do wee what we can do, ſinne will alwayes be a Iebuzite, a falſe borderer, yea a ranck traytor rebelling againſt the ſpirit. Which makes the life of man firſt to bee, ſaies Chryſoſtom, <hi>a debt</hi> (as it were) owne &amp; due <hi>to death</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>. For the diuell is the father of ſin, and ſin is the mother of death. Hereupon Sainct Iames ſaies, that ſin beeing finiſhed tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailing in childbyrth like a mother brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth forth death. And Dauid in the ninth pſalme calleth ſin the gate of death. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as a man comes into a houſe by the gate: ſo death came into the world by ſinne. The corruption of our fleſhe did not make the ſoule ſinfull: but the ſinne of our ſoule did make the fleſh corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Wherupon Lactantius calleth ſin the reliefe or the foode of death<note n="h" place="margin">Pabulum mortis.</note>. As a fier goeth out, when all the fuell is ſpent, but burneth, as long as that laſteth: ſo death dieth when ſin ceaſeth, but where ſin aboundeth there death rageth. The Prophet Abacucke ſinning not, death was ſo far from him that he was able to flie without winges: but king Aſa ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, death was ſo neere to him that he
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:174760:36"/>was not able to ſtand vpon his feet. Nay wee may ſee this in one &amp; the ſelfeſame ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Moyſes ſinning not death could not meet with him in the bottome of the red ſea: but ſinninge death did ſeaze vpon him in the top of mount Nebo. So that the life of man by reaſon of his ſin is <hi>the life of death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is alſo <hi>the life of the deuill.</hi> As Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenus ſayes, Each one hath in him as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deuils as euils<note n="i" place="margin">Tot daemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia quot cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina.</note>: euery ſeuerall ſinne being ſufficient to maintaine a ſeuerall deuill. The godly finding no ioy in the earth, haue their conuerſation in heauen. But Sathan finding no ioy in hell, hath his conuerſation in the earth. So that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth is a hell to vs; but a heauen to him. Here hee hath his liuing. As it was ſaid at the firſt, Thou ſhalt eate the duſt of the earth all the daies of thy life. This duſt, ſayes Macarius, is the deuils dyet<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as a ſcadle curre waites for a bone: ſo hee that goes about ſeeking whom he may deuour, watches continually till the godly ſhake off the duſt from their feet, that is, ſhake off ſome ſinne which they haue gotten by walking in the worlde, that then hee may licke it vp as one of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:174760:37"/>thoſe dogs, which did licke vp Iezabels bloud. This is meate and drinke to him<note n="l" place="margin">Dulce diabolo peccare nos. Hila. Enarra. in p. <hi>118.</hi>
               </note>. He loues it a life to ſee vs ſinne, euen as curſed Cham did to ſee Noahs nakednes. And as flies are alwaies buſie about a ſore place: ſo, ſayes Theophilact<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. In cap. Luk. <hi>16.</hi> p. <hi>320.</hi>
               </note>, That is a ſport or a pleaſure to Sathan, which is a ſore or a paine to man. Eſpecially if he be a godly man. For this Behemoth the deuill <hi>eateth graſse as an oxe</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Iob. 40.10.</note>. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Gregory noteth, that a ſheepe or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch other beaſt will eate any manner of graſſe, though it be trampled and ſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned neuer ſo much: but an oxe will eate no kind of graſſe but that which is green and freſh. And ſo the deuill will be ſure to haue his feede of the very fineſt and beſt<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſca eius e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecta.</hi> Abacuc. 1.16.</note>. For the angell of the Lord reioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth moſt when one that is a ſinner con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerteth. He eateth graſſe as a ſheepe. But the angel of ſathan reioyceth moſt, when one that is a conuert ſinneth. Hee eateth graſſe as an oxe. If the deuill can not keepe a man from liuing long, then hee will hinder him from liuing well<note n="p" place="margin">Aut impetrat mortes aut im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petit mores. Leo.</note>. If hee can not kill him, then hee will corrupt him. And indeede hee takes greater pleaſure in corrupting one god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:174760:37"/>man, then in killing a hundred wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. He was more delighted when Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid ſlew but Vrias, then when Saul ſlew himſelfe: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Peter did but deny Chriſt, then when Iudas betrayed him. So that the life of man by reaſon of his ſin is the delight, yea it is the very <hi>life of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is on th'other ſide <hi>the death of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</hi> O miſerable wretch that I am (ſaies one) who ſhall deliuer me from this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of death? The life of the godly is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry body of death. But their death is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a ſhadow of death. Thales a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher being demaunded what difference there is betweene life and death? Anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, They are all one. Then being asked againe, if he had not rather liue, then die? No, ſaies he, as before, for they are al one. But Ierome ſaies farre more excellently, They are not all one. That is not true. For it is one thing to liue in continuall daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of death: an other thing to die in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall aſſurance of life<note n="q" place="margin">Aliud viuere morituru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ud mori victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</note>. Therefore Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtes ſaies, that the day of our death is better then the day of our birth. For when we are borne we are mortall: but when we are dead we are immortal. And
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:174760:38"/>wee are aliue in the wombe to die in the world: but wee are dead in the graue to liue in heauen. Hence it is that the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked are merrie at their birth day, as Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh made a feaſt at his birth day, when his chiefe baker was hanged<note n="r" place="margin">Gen. 40.20.</note> and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod likewiſe made a feaſt at his birth day whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iohn Baptiſt was beheaded: but they are ſory at their dying day, as Iudas was ſorie when he went about to hang him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: &amp; Cain was afraid euery one would kill him that met him. Contrariwiſe the godly are ſory at their birth day, as Iob, Let the day periſh wherein I was borne: and Ieremie, Let not the day wherin my mother bare me be bleſſed<note n="ſ" place="margin">Ierem. 20.14.</note> But they are merrie at their dying day, as Simeo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Lord now letteſt thou thy ſeruant depart in peace: &amp; Paul, I deſire to be diſſolued &amp; to be with Chriſt. Therfore we alſo keep holy daies, and celebrate the memorie of the Saints not vpon their birth-daies, but vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their death-daies, to ſhew that theſe two are not all one, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the day of our death is better then the day of our birth. For whereas there are two waies, the one hauing in it, firſt a tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſitory life, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an eternall death, the other hauing in it firſt
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:174760:38"/>a tranſitory death, &amp; then an eternall life: the wicked chooſe to liue here for a time, though they die for it hereafter eternally, but the godly chooſe to haue their life hid with Chriſt here, that they may liue with Chriſt eternally hereafter. Therefore the wicked neuer think of death; but the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly think of nothing els. As Alexander the monarch of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world had al other things, ſaue only a ſepulchre to bury him in whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was dead; he neuer thought of that. But Abraham the heire of the world had no other poſſeſſion of his own, but only a field which he bought to bury his dead <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; he thought of nothing elſe. We read that Daniel ſtrowed aſhes in the temple to deſcrie the footeſteps of Bels prieſts, which did eate vp the meate. So did A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham ſtrow aſhes in his memorie, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I will ſpeake vnto my Lord though I bee but duſt and aſhes. So doe all the faithfull remembring they ſhall one day be turnde to duſt and aſhes. That ſo ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and marking the footeſteps of death how it continually commeth and ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth away their ſtrength (as Bels prieſts did the meate) how it dayly eateth vp &amp; waſteth and conſumeth their life, they
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:174760:39"/>may be alwaies prepared for it. Our firſt parents made them garments of figge leaues. But God miſliking that gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> garmentes of skinnes. Therefore Chriſt in the Goſpell curſed the fig tree which did beare onely fig leaues to couer our ſinne: but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended the Baptiſt which did weare skins to diſcouer our mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. For not onely, as Auſtin ſayth, Our whole life is a diſeaſe<note n="t" place="margin">Vita morbus.</note>: but alſo as Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard ſaith, Our whole life is a death<note n="u" place="margin">Vita mors.</note>. The life of man by reaſon of his ſinne is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall diſeaſe, yea it is the very <hi>death of himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is laſtly <hi>the death of Chriſt.</hi> The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Eſay calleth Chriſt a ſin, or a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for ſinne<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aſham.</hi> Eſay 53.10.</note>, prefigured by all thoſe ſin-offerings of the old lawe. Becauſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede when Chriſt was crucified at the firſt, he was broken for our ſinnes. Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that of Tertullian,<note n="y" place="margin">Propter pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum mori neceſſe habuit filius dei. Vide etiam Aug. Medita. cap. <hi>7.</hi> vbi docet hominem eſſe cauſam paſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</note> Sinne it was which brought the ſonne of God to his death. The Iewes were only inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts and acceſſaries to it: ſinne was the ſetler and the principall. They cryed, <hi>Crucifie him</hi> in the courte of Pilate: but our ſins cryed, <hi>Crucifie him</hi> in the court of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Now as the death of Chriſt was not
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:174760:39"/>efficient to ſaue the wicked: ſo the ſinne of the wicked was not ſufficient to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne Chriſt. But the ſcripture ſayth of them which either are, or at leaſt wiſe ſeeme to bee godly, They ſay they know God, but by their works they deny him: and, Saul, Saul, why doſt thou perſecute me? and, They crucifie again vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the ſonne of God. Zacharie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecieth of Chriſt,<note n="*" place="margin">Zach. 13.6.</note> That when one ſhall ſay vnto him, what are theſe wounds in thy hands? Then he ſhall anſwere, Thus was I wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in the houſe of my frends. That is, in the houſe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ought to haue bin my friends. So that our ſins did wound Chriſtes bandes at the firſt. And now alſo not the wicked, which are no part of his bodie, but wee which are myſtical members of his bodie, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhuld by good reaſon be his frends: we I ſay, do yet oftentimes by our ſinnes deny Chriſt with Peter: nay wee perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute Chriſt with Paul: nay wee crucifie Chriſt with the Iews. Yea (if it wil pleaſe you to heare me) I will ſay yet more, we crucifie Chriſt farre more cruelly then the Iews did. Then his body was paſſible and mortall, now it is glorified and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall;
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:174760:40"/>they knew not what they did, we doe ill enough, yet wee knowe what we doe well enough: they pearced him with a ſpeare, we pearce him with repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; they buried him in the earth, wee burie him in obliuion; then he roſe again the third day: but we ſo burie Chriſt, that not once in three dayes, no not once in three weekes he ariſeth or ſhineth in our hearts. Nay, that which I am aſhamed to ſpeake, though ſome are not aſhamed to doe it, there are in the world which haue no time, not once in three moneths, not once in three yeeres, no not once ſearch in their whole life to thinke of Chriſt, but burie him in the perpetuall forgerfulnes of their careles conſcience, as in a barren land, where all good things are forgotten. Wherefore let euery one as ſoone as hee is tempted to any ſinne, thinke ſtraightwaies that he ſees Chriſt comming towards him, wrapt vp in white linnen cloathes as he was buried, with a kercher bound about his head, and crying after a gaſtly and fearefull ſort, Beware, Take heede what you doe, Deteſt ſinne, abhorre ſin, Fie vpon it, A ſhame light on it, It once did moſt vilely
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:174760:40"/>and vilanouſlie murther mee: but now ſeeing my woundes are whole againe, do not (I beſeech you) do not rubbe and reuiue them with your ſinnes to make them bleed afreſh: now ſeeing the ſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the kingdome of heauen is put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my hand, doe not offer mee a reede a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to mocke mee: now ſeeing my head is crowned with the pure golde of eternall glorie, doe not ſet a crowne of thornes vpon it againe: now ſeeing I my ſelfe am enſtalled in the throne of the right hand of maieſtie, doe not pull me out of my throne, and throw mee into the graue againe, and with your ſinnes ſeale a mightie great ſtone vpon mee, to stiffle me, and preſſe me, and holde mee down in death. O beloued, good beloued at his inſtance be perſwaded, by whoſe bloud you are redeemed. Haue pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, haue pitie vpon poore Ieſus. Once he voluntarily yea euen ioyfully dyed for vs, and if that one death had not bin ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, he would haue bin content then to haue dyed a thouſande deaths more. Now he proteſteth, that the leaſt ſinne of any one Chriſtian, doth more vex him euen at the very heart, then all his dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:174760:41"/>paynes vpon the croſſe. Our ſinnes are thoſe ſouldiers which take him, thoſe tormentors which whippe him, thoſe thorns which gore his head, thoſe nayles which pearce his feete, that ſpeare which ſheds his bloud, that croſſe which takes away his life. And yet if to greeue him thus continually would do vs any good, then hee would bee moſt glad to prefer our good, though neuer ſo little, before his owne griefe, though neuer ſo great. But it is not ſo. That one death which he willingly ſuffered, was for our ſaluation. Theſe diuers deaths which wee without ſinnes ſo often put him to againſt his wil, do make for our greater da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he beſeecheth vs, &amp; I alſo being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate at the very feet of euery one of you heartely in his name exhorte you, if wee will haue no pity of him, yet for the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der loue wee beare to our owne deare ſoules, that we would not alwaies keepe him vppon the racke, and euery daye vex this iuſt Lot with our vnlawfull deedes, that we would not any more ſhead his precious bloud, and tread it and tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple it vnder our feete. This I aſſure you (bleſſed Chriſtians) will be a moſt forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:174760:41"/>meanes, not only to terrifie and fraye vs from ſin which we may commit here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, but alſo to mollifie and melt our harts for ſin which we haue committed heretofore, if we conſider, that the life of man by reaſon of his ſin is <hi>the death of Chriſt.</hi> Thus you ſee that the life of man, <hi>is the life of death: the life of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill: the death of himſelfe: the death of Chriſt.</hi> And therefore he ſaith in this fift part, weepe not too little for your owne life, FOR YOVR SELVES, WEEPE NOT FOR ME, BVT VVEEP FOR YOVR SELVES.</p>
            <p>THe ſixt part is next, FOR ME FOR YOVR SELVES. Which noteth, ſeeing both the exceſſe and the want are to bee eſchewed, that therefore the true meane which wee muſt keepe betweene Chriſt and our ſelues, conſiſteth in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne qualification of theſe two extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, FOR ME FOR YOVR SELVES both together. Weepe not too much, ſaith he, for my death, which is <hi>the death of death:</hi> weep not too little for your own life, which is <hi>the life of death.</hi> Not too to much for my death, which is <hi>the death
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:174760:42"/>of the diuell:</hi> not too little for your owne life, which is <hi>the life of the diuell.</hi> Not too much for my death, which is <hi>my life:</hi> not too little for your owne life, which is <hi>your death.</hi> Not too much for my death, which is <hi>the life of man:</hi> not too little for your owne life, which is <hi>the death of Christ.</hi> Saint Paul willeth the Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to approue themſelues by honor and diſhonor. Firſt by honour, then by diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. Teaching thereby that diſhonora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble honor is better then honorable diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. Yet to keepe a meane in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that we muſt as well count it an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, to bee ſometimes diſhonored with Chriſt, as a diſhonor to bee alwaies ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored without Chriſt. Euen ſo ſayes our Sauiour here FOR ME FOR YOVR SELVES. Firſt FOR ME, then FOR YOVR SELVES. Teaching thereby that to reioyce for Chriſt is better then to weepe for our ſelues. Yet to keepe a meane betwixt both, that we muſt aſwel ſometimes deſcend out of Chriſt into our ſelues to weepe, as alwaies aſcend out of our ſelues into Chriſt to reioyce. For the Apoſtle ſayes, that we muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce with them that reioyce and weepe
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:174760:42"/>with them that weepe. If my friend bee alwaies ſorowfull and neuer ioyfull, hee hath no pleaſure by me, if he be alwayes ioyful &amp; neuer ſorowful, I haue no proofe of him, but he is my deareſt friend, moſt delighted in mee, beſt approued by me, that takes ſuch part as I doe, ſometimes reioyſing, and ſometymes weepinge, reioyſing when I reioyce, and weeping when I weepe. The like is to bee ſeene in this place. FOR ME FOR YOVR SELVES. If a Chriſtian alwaies thinke of his owne miſerie and neuer of Chriſts mercie, hee will deſpayre: if hee alwayes thinke of Chriſts mercy and neuer of his owne miſery, hee will preſume. But hee is the beſt Chriſtian, ſo hye, that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deſpayre, ſo low, that he cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, which inclines aſwell to the one as to the other, ſometimes reioyſing and ſometimes weeping; reioyſing for Chriſt and weeping for himſelfe. A man cannot weepe too little for Chriſt, if he preſume not: a man cannot weepe too much for himſelfe, if he deſpayre not. But he may eaſily deſpayre, that weeps too much for Chriſt: and he may eaſely preſume, that weeps too little for himſelfe. Wherefore
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:174760:43"/>as in a ballance, if there be any ods in the ſcales we take out of that which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uier, &amp; put into that which is the lighter, til there be no difference betwixt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: So here we muſt waye theſe matters well, that wee our ſelues may be iuſt waight, neither too heauie for our owne miſerie, nor too light for Chriſts mercy. Thus did Dauid when he ſayd to God, <hi>Hyde mee vnder the ſhadowe of thy winges.</hi> What are Gods wings? His mercy &amp; his iuſtice. What is the ſhadowe of his winges? Our loue and our feare. Our loue is the ſhadow of his mercie, which is his right winge. Our feare is the ſhadowe of his iuſtice, which is his left wing. Now ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he that is hid vnder the right winge only maye preſume becauſe hee hath no feare, and hee that is hid vnder the left winge only may deſpayre, becauſe hee hath no loue, therefore ſaieth Dauid, Hide me, O Lord, vnder the ſhadowe, not of one winge, but of both thy winges. That I maye neuer deſpayre while I alwaies loue thy mercy, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce for Chriſt: that I may neuer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume while I alwaies feare thy iuſtice and weepe for my ſelfe. A Quaile the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:174760:43"/>ſame bird which was the Iſraelites meate in the wildernes, as he flyes ouer the ſea, feeling himſelfe begin to be wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie lightes by the way into the ſea. Then lying at one ſide, hee layes downe one wing vpon the water, and holdes vp the other wing towards heauen. Leaſt hee ſhould preſume to take too long a flight at the firſt, he wets one wing. Leaſt hee ſhould deſpayre of taking a new flight afterwardes, hee keepes the other wing drye. Thus muſt a chriſtian man doe. When he layes downe the wing of feare vpon the water to weepe for himſelfe, then he muſt holde vp the wing of loue towards heauen to reioyce for Chriſt. That his two wings may be anſwerable to Gods two wings. That as God hath two wings, the one of mercy, the other of iuſtice: ſo hee may haue two wings, the one of ioy for Chriſt, the other of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for himſelfe. Shem and Iapheth No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah godly and dewtifull children, when they ſawe their father otherwiſe then hee ſhould be, went backeward and couered him. They went backeward, that they might not ſee him themſelues: they co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered him, that others might not ſee
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:174760:44"/>him. Chriſt hanging naked vpon the croſſe, was <hi>the ſhame of men, &amp; the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cast of the people.</hi> Therefore we that are the children of God muſt goe backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward by abhorring them that crucified Chriſt: and yet we muſt couer him and hide him, euen in our very hearts, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring and honoring his death and reſurrection. Leaſt we ſhould preſume, wee muſt goe backeward for feare: and yet leaſt wee ſhould deſpayre, wee muſt couer him for loue. That as God hideth vs vnder the ſhadow of his wings which are loue, and feare, loue the ſhadow of his mercie, and feare the ſhadowe of his iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: ſo wee may hide God vnder the ſhadowe of our wings, which are ioye, and ſorrow, ioy the ſhadow of our loue, and ſorrow the ſhadowe of our feare, ioy for Chriſt, and ſorrow for our ſelues. To this ſtrange kinde of going backward, the Pſalmiſt alludeth when hee ſaith to God, <hi>Thou haſt made my feete like hines feete.</hi> A hine goeth not ſtill forward in one way, but as an auncient father ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, hee iumpes croſſe out of one way into another<note n="z" place="margin">Saltum habet tranſuer ſum.</note> Right ſo a chriſtians feete muſt be like hines feete. He muſt iumpe
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:174760:44"/>croſſe, from himſelfe to Chriſt, and then backe againe, from Chriſt to himſelfe. Would you ſee ſuch a hine? Then marke how Iob footes it. That he might not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpayre, he iumpes croſſe from himſelfe to Chriſt, and ſayes<note n="a" place="margin">Chap. 33.9.</note>, I am cleare without ſinne, I am innocent, and there is none i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niquitie in mee. Here is the mercie of Chriſt. But that hee might not preſume, bee iumpes backe againe from Chriſt to himſelfe, and ſayes<note n="b" place="margin">Chap. 6.2.</note>, O that my griefe were well wayed, and that my miſeries were laide together in the ballance. Here is the miſery of man. Thus muſt we way the mercy of Chriſt, and the miſerie of man together in the ballance, and be ſure (as I ſayde before) wee make the ſcales euen, and when wee waie the reaſons why wee ſhould not weepe for Chriſt, then wee muſt way the reaſons alſo why we ſhould weepe for our ſelues. So wee ſhal finde, for great cauſe of ioy in Chriſt, great cauſe of ſorrow in our ſelues: for greater cauſe of ioye in Chriſt, greater cauſe of ſorrow in our ſelues: for grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt cauſe of ioye in Chriſt, greateſt cauſe of ſorrow in our ſelues: for that which is more then all to make vs ioyfull in
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:174760:45"/>Chriſt, that which is more then all to make vs ſorrowfull in our ſelues. The righteouſnes of Chriſt is <hi>the death of death.</hi> Great cauſe of ioye in Chriſt. If Debora reioyced when Barack put Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſera to flight, haue not we as great cauſe to reioyce, ſeeing Chriſt hath put death to flight? The ſinne of man is <hi>the life of death.</hi> Great cauſe of ſorrowe in our ſelues. If Anna wept for her barrennes, haue not we as great cauſe to weepe, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wee can conceiue nothing but ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, &amp; bring forth iniquity vnto death? The righteouſnes of Chriſt is <hi>the death of the diuell.</hi> Greater cauſe of ioy in Chriſt. If Iudith reioyced, when ſhee did cut off the head of Holofernes, haue not wee greater cauſe to reioyce, ſeeing Chriſt hath cut off the head of the diuell? The ſinne of man is <hi>the life of the diuell.</hi> Greater cauſe of ſorrowe in our ſelues. If Thamar wept being defloured by her brother, haue not wee greater cauſe to weepe ſeeing wee commit ſpirituall inceſt and adulterie daylie with the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell? The righteouſnes of Chriſt is <hi>the life of himſelfe.</hi> Greateſt cauſe of ioye in Chriſt. If Sara laught when ſhee
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:174760:45"/>hearde ſhee ſhould haue a quicke childe in her dead wombe, is not this the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt cauſe of laughter which can bee vnto vs, that Chriſt liued in death, and was moſt free among the dead, and could not ſee corruption in the graue? The ſinne of man is <hi>the death of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</hi> Greateſt cauſe of ſorrowe in our ſelues. If Agar wept being turnde out of Abrahams houſe, is not this the greateſt cauſe of weeping, which can be vnto vs, that our life is no life, becauſe wee neuer ceaſe from ſinning, while wee are here pilgrimes and ſtrangers exiled and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed out of our fathers houſe in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen? The righteouſnes of Chriſt <hi>is the life of man.</hi> This is more then all to make vs ioyfull in Chriſt. If Queene Eſter did reioyce, as Queene Elizabeth doth at this daye (whom God for his mercies ſake euer ſaue and preſerue, and let al the people ſay <hi>Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi>) becauſe ſhe deliuered her people from thraldome and deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, can anye thing in the world then make vs more ioyfull then this, that we being curſed in our ſelues are bleſſed in Chriſt, being embaſed in our ſelues are exalted in Chriſt, being condemned in
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:174760:46"/>our ſelues are iuſtified in Chriſt, being dead in our ſelues are aliue in Chriſt? The ſinne of man is <hi>the death of Chriſt.</hi> This is more then all to make vs ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in our ſelues. If the virgine Mary wept ſo ſore for the death of her ſonne Ieſus, as though her tender heart had bin ſtabde and pearſt thorough with a ſharp ſworde (as Simeon ſpeaketh) can any thing in the worlde then make vs more ſorrowfull, then this, that Chriſt being bleſſed in himſelfe, was curſed for vs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exalted in himſelfe was embaſed for vs, being iuſtified in himſelfe, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for vs, being aliue in himſelfe, was dead for vs? O deare brother, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Chriſtian, whoſoeuer thou art, if thou bee too ſorrowfull at any time, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what Chriſt hath done for thee; how louingly; how kindely he hath dealt with thee, and thou wilt ſoone be glad: if thou bee too ioyefull at any time, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what thou haſt done againſt Chriſt; how vngratefully; how wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chedly thou haſt dealt with him, &amp; thou wilt ſoone be ſorry. So ſhall wee neuer ſuffer ſhipwrack of fayth, either by too much ſorrowe, as Eſau did, who ſought
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:174760:46"/>the bleſſing <hi>with teares,</hi> weeping for himſelfe, not reioycing for Chriſt: or els by too much ioye as Herod did, who heard the Baptiſt <hi>gladly,</hi> reioycing for Chriſt, not weeping for himſelfe. But e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as a ſhip being neither too heauily burdened, not too lightly balanced, ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth neither waues nor windes, but ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth ſafely to the heauen: ſo we being nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther too heauy for our own miſerie, nor too light for Chriſts mercy, but ioyning FOR ME FOR YOVR SELVES both together, ſhal neither be drowned with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waues of deſperatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor puffed vp with the winds of preſumption, but we ſhall ſayle ſafely in the arke of Noah vpon the fea of this world till wee ariue at the hauen of all happines in heauen. And this is the right moderation wee muſt keepe betwene Chriſt and our ſelues, as appeareth in this ſixt part, FOR ME FOR YOVR SELVES both together, VVEEPE NOT FOR ME BVT VVEEPE FOR YOVR SELVES.</p>
            <p>THe ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th part followeth, VVEEP NOT FOR MEE. Wherin we muſt condſider three vertues that were in Chriſt. <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome;
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:174760:47"/>benignity; magnanimity.</hi> For <hi>wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> he ſayth, VVEEPE NOT: for <hi>benig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nty,</hi> NOT YOV; for <hi>magnanimity,</hi> NOT FOR ME. Not weepe: not you: not for me. VVEEPE NOT FOR ME. Firſt for <hi>wiſdome</hi> he ſaith VVEEPE NOT. S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin hath a very excellent ſentence. And it is this<note n="d" place="margin">Crux Chriſti pendentis, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedra fuit docentis.</note> Chriſt vpon his croſſe did read vs a lecture, like a doctor in his chaire. Indeed in that learned lecture of his hee deliuered vnto vs many notable poynts of wiſdome. And one eſpecially wee haue here. Whereby wee are inſtructed how we ſhould be affected towards the dead. For if we muſt not weepe immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratly for the death of Chriſt, then wee muſt not greeue our ſelues greatly for the death of any chriſtian. The ancient Italians vſed to mourne for their dead ten monthes: the Egiptians ſeaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty two daies: the Ethiopyans fourty dayes: the auncient Germaines thirty daies: the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedemonians a leuen daies<note n="e" place="margin">Iohannes Bahemus de morib. Gen</note>. But the Athenians &amp; the Romanes, which were in their time coumpted the wiſeſt men in the world, were much more moderat. For the Athenians had a law giuen them by Solon their lawgiuer, which did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:174760:47"/>mourning at burials. The Romanes likewiſe had a law in their twelue tables, which did forbid to make any exclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or outcries at funerals<note n="f" place="margin">Leſſum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere funeris ergô.</note>. Yea the third counſel holden at Toledo in ſpaine the one &amp; twentieth canon of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel flatly decreeth, that chriſtians ſhould bee brought to their graues only with ſinging &amp; reioycing<note n="g" place="margin">Cum canti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis ſolummodo &amp; pſallent iu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>vocib.</note>. Becauſe, quoth the councel, the apoſtle to the Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians ſaies, I wil not haue you ignorant brethren concerning them which are iſleepe that you ſorro we not, euen as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers which haue no hope. Therfore Cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertus, who was Archbiſhop of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bury longe before the conqueſt<note n="(h)" place="margin">Floruit regnante Eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berto. Anno Domini. <hi>747.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his death charged that no lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhould be made for him. And Ierom writeth, that when the dead body of Paul the Eremite was brought forth, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Anthony did ſing hymnes &amp; pſalmes according to the chriſtian<note n="(i)" place="margin">Prolato fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras corpore Hymnos &amp; Pſalmos de chriſtiana tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditione decan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabat. In vita Pauli Erems.</note> tradition. And that when Paula a deuout widowe was<note n="(k)" place="margin">Pontifices choros pſallen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium duceba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. In Epitaphio Paulae.</note> buried the biſhops did bring her forth with ſinging. And that when Fabiola was buried, pſalmes were ſong &amp; <hi>Haleluiah</hi> was chaunted out ſo loud, that it did ſhake the ſeelinge of the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:174760:48"/>church<note n="(l)" place="margin">Sonabant pſalmi &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rata templo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum reboans in ſublime quatiebat Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leluia. In Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphio Fabiolae. Vide praeterea Sulpitium in vita Martini Ariopag. Et Eub. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare. eccleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note>. Igraunt indeed we may ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe and weep for the wicked not only when they are dead, but euen when they are aliue. But wee muſt ſing and reioyce for the godly not only when they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, but euen when they are dead. And why? Becauſe they beeinge aliue are dead: but theſe beeing dead are aliue. According to that ſaying of the hebrew Rabbins<note n="m" place="margin">Tſaddikim bemetham caijm &amp;c.</note> The godly euen in their death are aliue: but the wicked euen in their life, are dead. Therfore Dauid whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ſon Abſalon died, whom he knew to bee a wicked man wept for him, ſaying, Abſalon my ſon, O my ſonne Abſolon! would to God I had died for thee. But when his yong ſon died, whom he knew to be an innocent babe, hee was well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payd, and aroſe from the ground, and annoynted his face, and looked cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and ſayd, I ſhall goe to him, he can not returne to me. Wherby he warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth that of Fulgentius who ſayth, That the godly deceaſed are<note n="n" place="margin">Non amisſi ſed praemisſi.</note> not loſt for euer but left for a time, not gone away from vs, but ſent to God before vs. For if that bee true which Ignatius ſaies. That life without Chriſt is death<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this is true
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:174760:48"/>alſo which I ſhall ſay, That death with and in Chriſt is life. The deathes of the ſaints are no funerals but triumphes<note n="p" place="margin">Exercitia ſuntaſta non funera. Cypr.</note>. So that in reſpect of vs which are aliue it is a very charitable cuſtome, yea it is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry honorable cuſtome to giue mourning cloakes or gownes. But in reſpect of them that are dead it is altogether need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. For what neede wee weare black mourning cloakes in ſigne of forrowe, ſeeing (as it is in the Reuelation) they weare white long roabes in token of try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph. Therfore Chryſoſtome ſaith<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>, It becommeth vs that are chriſtians at the death of chriſtians, rather to reioyce as at a triumph, then to weep as at a tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy. For, ſaies Ierom<note n="r" place="margin">Deſiderandi ſunt vt abſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes non deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randi vt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tui.</note> We may indeed wiſh for them, becauſe they are not with vs; but we muſt not weepe for them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are with God. Loue, I graunt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunds vs. Well. Be it ſo. What then? But yet faith forbids vs to weepe for the dead<note n="ſ" place="margin">Pietas plora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re iubet, ſides pro defunctis lugere vetat Iſidorus.</note>. And therfore Paulinus ſaith<note n="t" place="margin">Salua fide pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etatis officia pendamus, ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua pietate fidei gaudia praefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramus.</note>, Though wee may notwithſtanding our faith, performe to the dead the dueties of loue, yet wee muſt firſt notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our loue, affoord to our ſelues the comforts of faith. So, if we ſhead ſome
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:174760:49"/>fewe teares which run ſoftly like the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Sylo, no force ſaies Ambroſe<note n="u" place="margin">Erunt non doloris illices ſed indices pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis.</note>, They will not bewray in vs any want of faith, but only teſtifie an abundance of loue. Thus and no otherwiſe did Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham weep for Sara his wife: Eleazar for Aaro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his father: Rebecca for Debora her nurſe: Ioſeph for Iacob his father: Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaba for Vrias her husband: Chriſt for Lazarus his friend. And here in wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>wiſdome</hi> he teacheh vs howe ſparing we ought to be in weeping for the death of our godly friendes, conſidering our good hope that are aliue, and their good happe that are dead. As if the very dead body whom ſome of you perhaps euen at this preſent ſo ſeriouſly thinke of, &amp; ſo much lament for, ſhould nowe ſodain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ariſe out of the graue, and ſtep into the pulpit, and preach and ſay vnto you, VVEEP NOT FOR ME BVT VVEEP FOR YOVR SELVES. You indeed as yet remaine in this vale of miſery, where you ſin daily and howerly againſt God: where continually you feele afflictions &amp; puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts dew to your ſins: where laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you are depriued of the glory of God: of the ſociety of the ſaintes: of the ioyes of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:174760:49"/>heauen. Therefore (if you will) VVEEP FOR YOVR SELVES, BVT VVEEPE NOT FOR MEE. I am in that ſtate of perfection, where I neuer ſin but alwaies prayſe and laud the Lord. I am out of the compas of all calamities, not to be touched with any trouble. Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore behold the amiable and the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing countenance of Chriſt: and though I come not very neere him, yet ſo farre forth I ſee him as this ſight alone is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to make mee euery way a happy man. Thus would the very dead, if they ſhould riſe againe, ſpeake vnto vs. But wee will not any longer diſquiet the dead, or diſturbe them which ſo ſweetly ſleep in Chriſt. Certainly either this that hath bin ſpoken will perſwade vs, or els (as our ſauiour ſaith) though one ſhould riſe ſtom the dead, wee would not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue. For if theſe auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; holy fathers Fulgentius, Ignatius, Cyprian, Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, Ierom, Iſidore, Paulinus, Ambro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius, ſhould now all ariſe, they would (I aſſure you) ſay no other thing, but euen as you haue heard them ſpeake already in thoſe ſentences and allegations which I haue quoted &amp; cited out of them. The
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:174760:50"/>ſum of all which is this, That it is great folly and childiſhnes to weep immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratly for the dead, and that it is on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide a hie point of <hi>wiſdome</hi> to bee moderate in this matter. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering our Lord going here to his death, teacheth his friends not to weepe for him, in that hee ſaies, VVEEP NOT, VVEEP NOT FOR MEE. Thus much for his <hi>wiſdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nowe for <hi>benignity</hi> hee ſaies, NOT YOV. For though the perſon bee not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the engliſhe, yet in the greek verbe it is implyed. Weepe not, as if it were, weepe NOT YOV. Which <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignity</hi> appeared in that among all his vntollerable troubles, nothing troubled him ſo much, as that his friends were troubled for his troubles. And yet (as it ſhould ſeeme) they of all other had grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt cauſe thus to bee grieued. All the people wept for Moyſes death: all Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt for Ioſephs death: all Iſrael for Ioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as his death: all the Church for Stephens death. But a million of Moyſeſſes: of Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephs: of Ioſiaſſes: of Stephens are not comparable to Chriſt. The women of Troy wept for the death of worthy He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor their valiant captaine, making this
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:174760:50"/>the foot of their doleful ditty, <hi>we weep for Hector</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Hectora fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Seneca in Troade. actu primo,</note>. Howe much more then ought theſe women of Ieruſalem to weepe for the death of their captaine Chriſt? Al the widowes lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted the death of Dorcas, becauſe in her life time ſhee made them coates and garments. And had not theſe women then far greater reaſon to lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the death of Chriſt who made euery one of them a wedding garment, wherin hee did marry them to himſelfe? Ye daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Iſrael ſaith Dauid, weep for Saul who clothed you with Scarlet. Howe much more then ought theſe daughters of Ieruſalem to weepe for Chriſt who cloathed euery one of them with ſcarlet, and with the royall robe of his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, yea and gaue his owne deare ſelfe vnto them, that they might put on the Lord Ieſus? When Chriſt was borne the night was turned into day, as it was propheſied<note n="y" place="margin">Pſalm. 139.12.</note>, Then ſhall the night ſhine as the day. But when Chriſt was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the day was turned into night, as it was propheſied<note n="z" place="margin">Amos cap. 8. ver. 9.</note>, Then ſhall the ſun go downe at noone day. The <hi>ſunne</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wept for Chriſt. As Hammons face was couered when he was condemned
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:174760:51"/>to die: ſo the ſuns face was couered, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt was condemned to die. The <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> alſo wept for Chriſt. As Dauid rent his garment when he heard of Ionathans death: ſo the temple rent his vaile when it heard of Chriſts death. The <hi>graues</hi> likewiſe wept for Chriſt. As the king of Niniue threw vp duſt vpon his head whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hee and his ſubiects were appointed to die: ſo the graues opened and threwe vp duſt vpon their heads when Chriſt was appoynted to die. The <hi>ſtones</hi> laſtly wept for Chriſt. As Iob cut his haire when hee heard of his childrens death: ſo the ſtones were cut in peeces and clouen aſunder when they heard of Chriſtes death. An aſſe carying Chriſt into Ieruſalem, the children ſung moſt merely: Chriſt cary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his croſſe out of Ieruſalem, the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men wept moſt mournfully. If thoſe children had held their peace and not ſung (as our ſauiour there proteſteth) the very ſtones would haue ſunge out the praiſe of Chriſt. If theſe women had held their peace, &amp; not cried, the very ſtones would haue cried for the death of Chriſt. Or rather indeed as ſoone as euer theſe women left weepinge, becauſe Chriſt
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:174760:51"/>bad them, ſtraightwaies the ſtones fell a weeping, before Chriſt bad them. And what heart of man then could here haue refrayned from weeping, though it had bin harder then any ſtone, ſeeing the hard ſtones before his eies thus diſſolued and diſtilled into teares? Yet behold the <hi>benignity</hi> and louing kindnes of Chriſt. Chriſt died, not for the <hi>ſunne:</hi> not for the <hi>temple:</hi> not for the <hi>graues:</hi> not for the <hi>ſtones:</hi> but for vs men and for our ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he dyed. Yet he ſuffereth theſe ſence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les creatures to weep and to haue a liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feeling of his death, though they had no benefit by his death. But beeing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent himſelfe to ſhed his deareſt and his beſt bloud for vs: yet will not ſuffer vs in recompence to ſhed ſo much as one lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle teare for him. No no, ſaies he, I will beare all the ſorrow, you ſhall haue only ioy: and though I dye and ſhed my ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry heart bloud for you, yet you ſhall not ſo much as weepe, or ſhed the leaſt teare for mee. NOT YOV, VVEEPE NOT FOR ME. Thus much for his <hi>benignity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly for <hi>magnanimity</hi> he ſaies, NOT FOR MEE. Straunge ſtoutnes and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage. Eſpecially in him that was other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:174760:52"/>ſo mild and ſo meeke a lambe. But here the cauſe &amp; quarell beeing ours, &amp; he fighting for the ſaluation of our ſouls, there is no rule with him, hee plaies the lyon wherſoeuer hee goes. For holding nowe in his hand the cup of trembling, and beeing ready to drinke vp the very dregs of it, yet neither his hand nor his heart trembleth. Ennius the poet, as Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teſtifieth, could ſay thus much, <hi>Let no man weep for my death</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Nemo me lacrymis deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret.</note>. And S. Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence the martyr, as Prudentius witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, <hi>Doe not weep for my departure</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Deſiſte diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſu meo fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum dolenter fundere.</note>. But as Ennius or any other pagan could neuer come neere chriſtians in true mag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nanimity: ſo S. Laurence or any other chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> could neuer come neere Chriſt. The bleſſed Apoſtle S. Paul of any that euer I heard of, commeth neereſt to him. Going toward Ieruſalem, what do you, ſaies hee, weeping &amp; breaking my heart, for I am ready not only to be bound but euen to die alſo for the name of the Lord Ieſus? Euen ſo ſaith Chriſt here, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther indeed not ſo, but a thouſand times more couragiouſly. Going out of Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, what do you (ſaies hee) weeping and breakinge my heart, for I am ready
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:174760:52"/>not only to bee bound, but euen to dye alſo for the ſaluation of man? He knewe well enough his paſſion would be a new kind of transfiguration vnto him. For at his transfiguration he was accompanied with his deare diſciples, Peter, Iames, and Iohn: but at his paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Peter denied him, Iames &amp; Iohn forſooke him. And there he was vpon mount Tabor which ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſweetly of hearbs and flowers: but here he was vpon mount Caluary which ſmelled loathſomly of bones and dead mens ſculs. And there his face did ſhine as the ſun: but here his face was couered, nay it was buffeted and ſpit vpon. And there his garments were white as the light: but here his garments were parted, nay they were like Ioſephs coate all em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brued in bloud, and hee himſelfe ſtript ſtarke naked. And there he was between two famous prophets Moiſes &amp; Elias: but here when they thought hee called for Elias to help him, Elias would not come, nay he was between two theeues, the one at his right hand, the other at his left. And there his father ſpake moſt ioyfully to him from heauen, This is my beloued ſonne in whom only I am plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed;
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:174760:53"/>but here hee ſcreeched moſt lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably to his father from the croſſe, My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me? Yet behold, behold the <hi>magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity</hi> of Chriſt. Chriſt knewe well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough before hand of all this fearefull &amp; horrible paſſion prepared for him, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he was not transfigured as before, but disfigured ſo as neuer was any man. Yet nothing could moue him. This coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes of his diſciples: this noyſomnes of the place: theſe diueliſhe buffets vpon his bare face: theſe bloudy wounds vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his naked body: theſe vile theeues: theſe hydeous ſcreeches, could not one whit daunt his heroicall heart. But euen as a noble champion hauing already had a legge and an arme ſlaſht off, when all the ſtage in admiration of his valour and manhood cryes, <hi>ſaue the man, ſaue the man,</hi> yet puts out himſelfe, and ſtanding vpon one legge, and ſtrikinge with one arme fights ſtill as ſtoutly as if he had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer bin hurt at all: ſo Chriſt hauinge bin ſcorned and ſcourged already, when the whole theater of heauen and earth wept for him, yea when the powers aboue the heauen came down, and the dead vnder
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:174760:53"/>the earth roſe vp to moue and pitty him, only he himſelfe would neither aske any fauour of others, nor yet ſhewe any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to himſelfe, but was very angry &amp; called him Sathan that gaue him ſuch counſell; Yea though all the ſaincts in heauen and earth did bleed at the very heart<note n="(c)" place="margin">Caelum &amp; terra compati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untur ei. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelmus in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo Euangel. ſermonis cap. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> in a manner as much as he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe did vpon the croſſe, to ſee ſo good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> man ſo ſhamefully deſpited, yet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could ſtay him but ſtill he went on forward as pleaſantly and as cheerefully is to any banket or feaſt, to this moſt ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ull and dreadfull death. O ſweet Ieſus, O my deare Lord, forgiue me, I humbly beſeech thee, for thy mercy ſake, forgiue me this one fault. Thou wilt neither weep thy ſelfe, nor yet ſuffer me to weep for thy death. But I am contrariwiſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected. Though I doe not ſee thee at this preſent led as a lambe to the ſlaughter, yet only meditating of thy death ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundred yeeres after, I can not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly refraine from weepinge. Yea by ſo much the more do I lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nt and mourn, by how much the more I ſee thee ioyfull &amp; glad. Come forth ye daughters of Sio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaies he<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Canticae.</hi> 3.11.</note>, and behold king Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:174760:54"/>the crown wherewith his mother crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him in the day of his mariage in the day of the gladnes of his heart. As if hee ſhould haue ſayd, come forth yee daughters of Ieruſalem and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Ieſus Chriſt, with the crowne of thornes, wherwith the ſinagogue of the Iewes crowned him in the day of his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and in the day of his death vpon the croſſe. He calleth the day of his paſſion the day of his mariage, and the day of his death vpon the croſſe the day of the glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his heart. Thus you ſee in this ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth part the <hi>wiſdome;</hi> the <hi>benignity:</hi> the <hi>magnanimity</hi> of Chriſt, in that hee ſayth, Not weep: not you: not for mee; VVEEP NOT FOR ME. VVEEP NOT FOR ME, BVT VVEEP FOR YOVR SELVES.</p>
            <p>THe eyght part, which is the laſt, now only remaineth. BVT VVEEPE FOR YOVR SELVES: wherein wee muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider likewiſe three virtues that ought to bee in vs. <hi>Deuotion: compunction: compaſſion.</hi> For <hi>deuotion,</hi> he ſayes, BVT VVEEPE. For <hi>compunction,</hi> BVT YOV. For <hi>compaſſion,</hi> BVT FOR YOVR SELVES. But weepe: but you: but for
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:174760:54"/>your ſelues. BVT VVEEP FOR YOVR SELVES. Firſt for <hi>deuotion</hi> he ſaith, BVT VVEEPE. <hi>Deuotion</hi> generally is a ſuper-naturall dexteritie, wrought by the holy Ghoſt in the heart of a deuoute man, whereby hee is made prompt and ready to performe all thoſe dewties, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine to the ſeruice of God. As a man may be ſayd to be deuout in preaching: deuoute in hearing: deuoute in making prayers: deuoute in giuing almes. But here eſpecially by <hi>deuotion</hi> I vnderſtand a certaine ſoftnes and tendernes of the heart, which oftentimes is reſolued into teares, conſidering the miſchiefes and miſeries of this world. For if Chriſt in this place wiſht them of Ieruſalem to weepe for themſelues, and did himſelfe elſe where weepe for Ieruſalem, ſaying, O Ieruſalem, Ieruſatem, how ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would I, but you would not? How much more then ought wee to weepe for the wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chednes of this world? They of Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem were caryed captiue into Babylon. That captiuitie of Babylon endured ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenty yeres, or threeſcore and ten yeres. Now iuſt ſo long laſteth our life. As the Pſalmiſt ſayes, The dayes of our life are
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:174760:55"/>threeſcore yeeres and ten. So that by this account, our whole time in this world, is nothing elſe but the captiuitie of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon. Therefore we may well ſay, By the waters of Babylon we ſate downe and wept, when wee remembred thee O Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And, My teares haue been my meate day and night, while they ſayd vnto me, where is now thy God? And, Woe is me that I am conſtrayned to dwell in Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhek, and to haue my habitation among the tents of Cedar. We reade that King Edward the third, hauing the King of Scots and the French King his priſoners here in England both together at one time, held royall iuſts in Smythfield. The iuſts being ended, hee feaſted both the Kings moſt ſumptuouſly at ſupper. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſupper perceiuing the French King to be ſad and penſiue, hee deſired him to be merry as others were. To whome the French King anſwered<note n="(e)" place="margin">Quomodo cantabimus cantica in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra aliena?</note>, How ſhall wee ſing ſongs in a ſtrange land? If the French King after all this princely pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtime, and ſtately intertainement, tooke it ſo heauily to heart, that hee was kept priſoner out of his owne countrey: how much more then ought wee to mourne
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:174760:55"/>for our captiuitie? Eſpecially ſeeing, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we haue ſuch welcome in the world as he had in England, neither yet is Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land ſo far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> France, as heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is diſtant from them both. Ieruſalem was once fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally ſacked by Titus and Veſpaſian, whereas beſides an infinite number which were otherwiſe ſpoyled, ten hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand men, ten hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men (I ſay) were ſlaine down right altogether, as Ioſephus a greeke writer, and Ioſippus an hebrew author teſtifie. But that which happened once to them, happeneth euery day to vs. We dye day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note n="(f)" place="margin">1. Cor. 15.31.</note>. Our whole life is nothing elſe but ſuch a ſpoyle and ſackage. And among all the miſeries of this life, nothing is more miſerable then this life it ſelfe. For euen thoſe things which might be moſt comfortable vnto vs, as we vſe them, do breede vs much ſorrow. Learning and knowledge a great delight. Yet Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſaith, Hee that addeth knowledge addeth ſorrowe. Wealth and riches a good complement. Yet Saint Iames ſayes, Goe too now you riche men, weep and houle for the miſeries which ſhall come vpon you. So that the onely hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:174760:56"/>we can haue in this life is a deuoute and a godly bewailing of our vnhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Which made our Sauiour ſay, woe be to you that laugh now, for you ſhall waile and weepe. But on the other ſide, Bleſſed are they that mourne now, for they ſhall bee comforted. Therefore holy Iob deſireth God to ſpare him a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and let him liue a while longer. Wherefore? That he might laugh? That he might be merry? No<note n="g" place="margin">Vt plangam delorem me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</note>, but, ſayes hee, That I may weepe for my woe and griefe. Hee thought a man could not haue time enough in this life, though it were neuer ſo long, to lament and rue the miſeries of this life, though it were neuer ſo ſhort. For if euery creature doe ſigh &amp; grone in it ſelfe<note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 8.22.</note> ; if the very earth which wee treade vnder our feete doe mourne and pine away in ſorrow, for the heauie burthen of our ſinnes wherewith it is almoſt wayed and preſſed downe to hell, how much more then ought we, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the firſt fruites of the ſpirit to haue alſo true <hi>deuotion</hi> in weeping for our miſerable eſtate in this world, according to this, BVT VVEEP, BVT VVEEP FOR YOVR SELVES. Thus much for our <hi>deuotion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:174760:56"/>
Now for <hi>compunction</hi> he ſayes, BVT YOV. The perſon is implyed in the greeke word, which ſignifies to weepe as they doe which haue a broken and a contrite heart<note n="(i)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> frango.</note>. Which weeping at the very heart is commanded in the fourth Pſalme. For whereas we commonly reade it, be ſtill in your chambers, the Septuagint inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret it, haue <hi>compunction</hi> in your cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. Now the hebrew word which they tranſlate, haue <hi>compunctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> doth ſignifie to be prickt to the quicke, till the bloud follow againe<note n="k" place="margin">Dommu à Dam ſanguis.</note>. And by chambers our hearts are ment. As, when thou prayeſt enter into thy chamber, that is, into the ſilence and ſecrecy of thine hart. So that, Haue <hi>compunction</hi> in your chambers, is as much as if he ſhould haue ſaid, Bleed you inwardly at the heart. Our teares muſt not be crocodiles teares. For as is praying from the teeth outward; ſo is weeping from the eyes outwarde. But ſaith Bernard, we muſt be let bloud, and haue a vayne opened with the launce of <hi>compunction</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Scindatur &amp; aperiatur vena ferro compun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionis. Ber. in ſerm. p. <hi>133.</hi>
               </note>. And this vayne alſo muſt not be the liuer vaine, or any other vaine, but the heart vaine onely<note n="m" place="margin">Non corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris ſed cordis. Fulgen.</note>. Whereupon Dauid ſaith, I roared for the very griefe
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:174760:57"/>of my heart<note n="n" place="margin">Pſalm. 38.8.</note>. And againe, My heart droppeth for heauines<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 119.28.</note>. Not that his heart dropt in deede. But becauſe the teares which he ſhed, were not droppes of water, running from the eyes which may be ſoone forced with onions or ſuch like, but drops of blood iſſuing from the heart, ſuch as Chriſt did ſweate in the garden. For theſe no doubte are trew teares, which are the blood of a woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded heart<note n="p" place="margin">Sanguis vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerati cordis. Aug. Epiſtola. <hi>199.</hi>
               </note>. So that the heart muſt firſt bee rent and deeply wounded before the eye canne vnfaynedly weepe. But in caſe our ſinnes fall vpon vs like theeues, and wounde vs at the very heart, &amp; leaue vs halfe dead, and make vs powre out the bloud of true teares, then by and by will Chriſt powre in the wine &amp; oyle of gladnes. Therefore ſayes a good father<note n="q" place="margin">Malo ſentire compunctio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem quàm ſcire defimito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</note> I had rather feele the touch of <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>punc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> then know the truth of a definition. For the heart of a Chriſtian being a while caſt downe in ſorrow is ſoone after ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp in ioye, and taketh his former <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction</hi> not as a punniſhment, but as a preferment, and is right glad to bee af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, becauſe he ſees, that as the more the waters did riſe the higher the arke
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:174760:57"/>was lifted vp; after the ſame ſorte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more his ſorrows encreaſe, the higher his heart is lifted vp to God<note n="r" place="margin">Cum per fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum mens ad ſumma rapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, compunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis ſuae paena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gaudons mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; libet affligi, quia af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictione ſua conſpicit ſe ad alta ſubleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri. Gregor.</note>. Wherupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ierom af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth that this <hi>compunctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> doth ſupple and ſoften our heartes, when it pierceth and afflicteth them<note n="ſ" place="margin">Dum pungit, vngit.</note>. Which we may ſee playnely in Saint Paule. All the while his heart was hardened &amp; ſeared with a hot yron, he playd the wilde colt (as I may ſay) without any remorſe or griefe kic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king againſt the pricks. But when it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God to take out of his breſt that hart of ſtone (to vſe the prophets words) and to giue him a heart of fleſh for it, then he did not any more kick againſt the prickes, but onely one <hi>ſtimulus carnis,</hi> the angell of ſathan, was ſufficient to bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle him, and tame him, and rule him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right. For euen as a bladder if it be prickt al the wind and emptines voydeth out of it: ſemblably Saint Paules holy heart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing prickt, and bleeding in wardly for his ſinnes was freed of all vanitie and pride, of all conceitednes and folly. Wherfore as the man of Iudea and Ieruſalem were pricked in their hearts<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Actorum.</hi> 2.37.</note>: ſo muſt we haue true <hi>compunction</hi> in bleeding and weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the heart, according to this, BVT
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:174760:58"/>YOV, BVT VVEEPE FOR YOVR SELVES. Thus much for our compunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Laſtly for <hi>compaſſion</hi> he ſayes BVT FOR YOVR SELVES. It is good to pitie others and to wipe awaye the very teares from their eyes with the ſpunge of <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Chryſ.</note>. So ſayes Iob<note n="x" place="margin">Iob. 30.25.</note>, Did I not weepe with him that was in trouble, and was not mine hart in heauines for the poore? But yet the greateſt <hi>compaſſion</hi> is to ſhew pity towards thy ſelfe. As Eccleſiaſticus ſayes,<note n="y" place="margin">Miſerere ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimae tuae pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens deo. c. <hi>30.</hi> v. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> Haue <hi>compaſſion</hi> on thine owne ſoule, if thou minde to pleaſe God. Thus did the publicane. Being moſt deſirous to pleaſe God, when he did pray to God, he ſayd, Lord be mercifull vnto me a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. The Phariſie was very ſory for the Publican, and ſayd, Lord I thanke thee, I am not as this Publicane. But the Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can was ſory for himſelfe. Euen as the high prieſt in the lawe did offer firſt for his owne ſinnes, and then for the ſinnes of the people<note n="z" place="margin">Hebr. 5.3.</note>: after the ſame faſhion this Publican did firſt offer the ſacrifice of prayer for his owne ſinnes, and then afterward he prayed for others. Therfore hee that durſt not lift vp his eyes to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:174760:58"/>did yet draw downe heauen to his eyes: and did enforce God alſo to haue <hi>compaſſion</hi> on him, becauſe hee had firſt <hi>compaſſion</hi> on himſelfe. For looke how Peters cocke did clap his own ſides with his wings, and wakened himſelfe before he wakened Peter: in like manner thou muſt ſmite thine owne breſt with the Publican, and clap thine own ſides with the cocke, before thou crie or crowe to others. Abrahams ſeruant did drinke himſelfe, before hee gaue his Camels drinke<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 24.19.</note>: right ſo the wiſe man aduiſeth thee<note n="b" place="margin">Prouer. 5.15.</note>, firſt for thy ſelfe, To drinke the waters of thy ceſterne, and the riuers in the middeſt of thine owne well; then for thy Camels, To let thy fountaines flowe forth, &amp; thy riuers of water in the ſtreets. Thou muſt firſt pledge Chriſt in his cup, and drinke one hearty draught of teares for thy ſelfe, and then thou maiſt drinke to others afterward. For if thine eye bee ſingle, all thy bodie is full of light. But if thou haue a beame in thine owne eye, and yet wouldeſt take a mote out of thy brothers eye, all thy body is full of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Whereas the way were firſt to weep out, and waſhe out that great beame
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:174760:59"/>which is in thine owne eye, that ſo thine eye being more ſingle, thou maiſt ſee cleerely to take a little mote out of thy brothers eye. Otherwiſe thou ſhalt bee like thoſe hagges or fayries (called in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine <hi>Lamiae</hi>) which we haue heard of in olde time, who (as they ſaye) could ſee well enough abroad, but when they came home, vſed to put vp their eyes in a boxe. And then Chriſt will ſay to thee, as he did to one elſewhere, <hi>Goe to thine owne houſe</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Abi in domu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tuam. Mar. <hi>5.29.</hi>
               </note>. Doe not prye into other mens faultes abroad, and put vp thine eyes in a boxe when thou art at home: but rather ſhut thine eyes abroad, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen them at home. Bee not like Crates Thebanus, who was called a <hi>doore-ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Laertius.</note>, becauſe hee vſed to ruſh into euery other mans houſe; &amp; there to finde faulte with whatſoeuer was amiſſe: but rather looke to thine own houſe, looke to thine own hart, weep for thine own life, weep for thine owne ſelfe. Many doe turne Chriſts, <hi>ſed vos pro vobis,</hi> into Virgils, <hi>ſic vos no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vobis.</hi> They can ſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble at a ſtrawe, and leape ouer a blocke. They can ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a Camell, &amp; ſtrayne a gnat. Though their owne backes be ſurcharged and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerloaden
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:174760:59"/>with ill fauoured lumpes of ſinne, like Camels bunches, yet their backes are broade enough to beare all that, they neuer feele it, they make no bones of it, they can ſwallowe it downe very well without any drinke of teares. But if they ſee no more then a little gnat ſitting vpon their brothers coate, by and by they finde a hole in his coate, they muſt needes (for ſooth) weepe for it, and alwaies vrge it, and preſſe it very ſore, and ſtrayne it thorough their teares. Such are the wicked ignorant Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, and other like factious Nouices of this age. They tell vs they weepe daylie for the ruine of Sion, &amp; for the deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Church. But our Church an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth them, as ſhee hath heard her ſpouſe Ieſus Chriſt ſaye in a like caſe, VVEEP NOT FOR ME, BVT VVEEP FOR YOVR SELVES. I, ſais our Church, was neuer more glorious in this realme of England heretofore<note n="(e)" place="margin">Foxus in prima conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratione ad Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtantes praeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xa Actis. Et in prima perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione primiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ae eccleſie p. <hi>32</hi>
               </note>, neuer am like to bee hereafter, then I am at this daye. And there is no one poynte of doctrine or diſcipline which I maintaine, that hath not beene within this fortie yeares confirmed, and beſprinkled, and euen
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:174760:60"/>enamuled with the very blood of as bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſaints, our owne deare countrymen, as holy martyrs as euer did holde vp in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent hands to God. Therfore VVEEPE NOT FOR ME. BVT VVEEP FOR YOVR SELVES. You in deede haue departed, not onely from this Church, of which you make ſo light: but alſo from the Primitiue Church, of which you talke ſo much. The order of the Primitiue Church is ſet downe in the Actes<note n="f" place="margin">Actorum. ca. <hi>2.</hi> v. <hi>46.</hi>
               </note>. They continued daylie with one accorde in the temple, and breaking bread at home, did eate their meate together with glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and ſinglenes of heart. So then in the Primitiue Church they continued daylie with one accord in the temple: you run out of the temple, and refuſe to praye with vs. In the Primitiue Church, they did breake breade at home: you breake peace abroad. In the Primitiue Church they did eate their meate together with gladnes and ſinglenes of heart: you haue turnde all ſinglenes into ſingularitie. You (ſayes our Church to the Browniſts) you are thoſe Donatiſts of whom Saint Auſtin ſpeaketh<note n="g" place="margin">Qui nobis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam oratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam impijs di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſput ationibus conantur au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re. E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i <hi>92.</hi> ad lanuarium.</note>, who by their impious arguments would take away from vs e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:174760:60"/>the Lordes prayer. So woulde the Browniſts. You are thoſe Neſtorians of whome Caſſianus ſpeaketh<note n="h" place="margin">Qui quia eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe nolunt quod omnes ſunt, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piunt omnes eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe quod ipſi vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunt. De incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natione. l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>4</hi>
               </note>, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they will not bee as all men are, therefore would haue all men be as they are. So would the Browniſts. You are thoſe Sectaries of whome Nazianzen ſpeaketh<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Apol. p. <hi>28</hi>
               </note>, who make a ſtirre about matters of no importance very vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly, and yet very impudently. So doe the Browniſts. You are thoſe ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes of whom Ireneus ſpeaketh<note n="k" place="margin">Qui propter modicas &amp; quaſlibet cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſas magnum &amp; glorioſum Christi corpus conſcindunt. l. <hi>4</hi> c. <hi>62.</hi>
               </note>, who for light and trifling quarrels, rent and teare the great and glorious body of Chriſt. So doe the Browniſts. You are thoſe Luciferians of whome Saint Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome ſpeaketh<note n="l" place="margin">Quibus fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liare est dicere factum de ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia lupanar. Dialo. contra. Luciferianos prope initium.</note>, who make it a common worde in their mouthes to ſaye that the Church is now become a ſtewes. So ſaye the Browniſts. You are thoſe heretikes of whom Bernard ſpeaketh<note n="m" place="margin">Qui omnes qui de eccleſia ſunt, canes cenſent &amp; por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos. Epistola. <hi>65</hi>
               </note>, who ſaye that all wee, or at the leaſt wiſe the moſt part of vs which are of the Church, are no better then dogges or hogges. So ſay the Browniſts. You are thoſe Audians of whome Epiphanius ſpeaketh<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Anchora, p. <hi>475</hi>
               </note>, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing buſie-bodies themſelues, and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in other mens dioces, yet thinke
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:174760:61"/>much that reuerend and learned Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops ſhoulde beare rule in their owne dioces. So doe the Browniſts. You are thoſe murmurers againſt Moyſes of whome Optatus ſpeaketh<note n="o" place="margin">Qui ante ſunt ſepulti quàm mortui. Contra. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. l. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>, who were buried before they were dead, becauſe they wepte for others before they wepte for themſelues. So doe the Browniſts. But to leaue theſe now, as they leaue the Churche, and to returne to our ſelues againe: wee that are Chriſtes louing friendes, and louing friendes alſo to his holy Churche, muſt weepe for none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo much as for our ſelues. That ſo we may continually practiſe, true <hi>deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> true <hi>compunction;</hi> true <hi>compaſſion;</hi> according to this, But weepe; but you; but for your ſelues; BVT VVEEPE FOR YOVR SELVES. VVEEPE NOT FOR ME, BVT VVEEP FOR YOVR SELVES.</p>
            <p>THus haue I gone ouer all the eight partes of this text. Now if I were as happy as Salomon was, that I might haue what ſo euer I would aske, I would, I aſſure you (beloued) deſire no greater gift of God at this time, then that wee might ſo meditate of this which hath bin
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:174760:61"/>ſpoken, as our whole life and all our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, eſpecially theſe affections of ioy and ſorrowe, which rule all the reſt, might therby be ordered and directed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right. For weeping, or not weeping, are things indifferent, ſimply of themſelues neither good nor bad, but thereafter as according to circumſtances and occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, they are either well or ill vſed. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as <hi>glorying:</hi> or <hi>laboring:</hi> or <hi>fearing:</hi> or <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uing.</hi> For <hi>glorying</hi> it is ſayd, Let not the wiſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> glory in his wiſdom, but let him that glorieth glory in this <hi>y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               </hi> he knoweth the Lord: For <hi>labouring</hi> it is ſayd, labour not for <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> meat which periſhth, but for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the meat which abideth for euer. For <hi>fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> it is ſayd, Feare not him that can kill the body only, but feare him who is able to deſtroy both body &amp; ſoule. For <hi>louing</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is ſayd, Loue not the world, nor the things of this world, if any man loue the world <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> loue of God is not in him. Now then, glory not, but glory. Not in the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the world, but in the knowledge of God. Labour not, but labour. Not for the meat which periſheth, but for the meat which abideth for euer. Feare not, but feare. Not him that can kill the body
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:174760:62"/>only, but him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> can deſtroy both body &amp; ſoule. Loue not, but loue. Not the world, but God. And ſo here, Weepe not, but weepe. Not for me, but for your ſelues. VVEPE NOT FOR ME, BVT VVEEP FOR YOVR SELVES. To weep is lawfull: to weepe without not weeping is vnlawfull. Not to weep is lawfull: not to weep without weeping is vnlawful. Again, To weep for your ſelues is lawfull: to weep immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratly for Chriſt is vnlawfull. Not to weep for Chriſt is lawfull: not to weep mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately for your ſelues is vnlawfull. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as without any vnlawfulnes in either, both weeping and not weeping wilbee lawfull. If your weeping be alwaies ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with not weeping; &amp; your not wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinge bee ſometimes ioyned with wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping. If your weeping be for your ſelues, not for Chriſt; and your not weeping be for Chriſt, not for your ſelues. Therefore wee muſt marke well, what our ſauiour ſayth. He ſaith not thus, <hi>weep not for me, &amp; weep not for your ſelues.</hi> That's too much ioy, &amp; too little ſorrowe. Neither thus, <hi>Weep for me &amp; weep for your ſelues.</hi> That's too much ſorrowe, and too little ioy. Neither thus, <hi>weep not for your ſelues,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:174760:62"/>but weep for mee.</hi> That's preſumptuous deſperation. Neither thus, <hi>weepe for me, but weep not for your ſelues.</hi> That's deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate preſumption. Only he ſaies thus, VVEEP NOT FOR ME, BVT VVEEP FOR YOVR SELVES. As if he ſhould haue ſayd, weep not too much: weepe not too much for my death: weep not much for my death. Nay, weepe little for my death: conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, my wiſdome; my benignity; my magnanimity; weepe little for my death. But weep not too little: but weepe not too little for your owne life: but weepe not little for your owne life. Nay, weepe much for your owne life: conſideringe, your deuotion; your compunction; your compaſſion; weep much for your owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe. Weepe little for my death, but weep much for your owne life. VVEEP NOT FOR ME, BVT VVEEP FOR YOVR SELVES.</p>
            <p>Wherfore holy brethren if wee haue any teares, nowe let vs ſhed them, if we haue any pſalmes, now let vs ſing them. The whole goſpel is nothing els but ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full newes, the ſum wherof is compriſed in that Euangelicall &amp; Angelicall meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to the ſhepherds, <hi>I bring you glad ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of great ioy, which ſhalbee to all
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:174760:63"/>people.</hi> But then Chriſt was borne in his mothers armes. Now he holdeth vp the Angels, that they fall not, and lifteth vp men, which are fallen, with his owne armes ſtretched out vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe. This Croſſe is his kingdome, that he carrieth vpon his ſhoulder<note n="(p)" place="margin">Eſa cap. 9. ver. 6.</note>, which is a grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter glory and credit to Chriſt then was the creation of the whole world<note n="(q)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Oecume. in cap. <hi>2.</hi> ad Heb.</note>. For if God had created a thouſand worlds, man had defaced them euery one with his ſin. But to ſaue if it be but one poore ſoule, and to redeeme it from the pit of hell, this indeede is the omnipotent po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the croſſe of Chriſt. Sweet ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, I humbly imbrace, and kiſſe the woundes of thy handes and feet: I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme more of thine hyſope, thy reede, thy ſpunge, thy ſpeare, then of any princely diadem: I boaſt my ſelfe &amp; am more proud of thy thornes and nailes, then of all pearles and iewels: I account thy croſſe more ſplendent and glorious then any royall crowne: tuſh what talke I of a crowne? then the very golden ſun beames in their greateſt beauty and brightnes. This is that triumph wherby Chriſt cauſed vs to triumph in himſelfe,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:174760:63"/>and to bee more then conquerours<note n="(r)" place="margin">2 Corin. cap. 2. ver. 4.</note>, when as the goodnes &amp; the ſweetnes of Chriſt did triumph ouer all impiety and malice<note n="ſ" place="margin">Cum de impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etate &amp; mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia ſuauitas piet aſque try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphauit. Cypr.</note>. And therfore if the women mette Dauid playing and ſinging, <hi>Saule hath ſlaine his thouſand, but Dauid his ten thouſand;</hi> howe much more then ought all the ſonnes and daughters of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, all chriſtian men and women, to meete Chriſt playing vpon the harpe, and ſinging that newe ſong to the lamb with the foure and twenty elders, Thou art worthy to receiue glory, and honor, and power, becauſe thou waſt killed, &amp; yet thou haſt killed, and ſlaine not only a thouſand or ten thouſand, but euen all thine and our enemies, and haſt redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vs thy friends to God by thy bloud? There is a time to weepe, and a time to laugh, a time to mourne, and a time to daunce<note n="(t)" place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 3. ver. 4.</note>. Why art thou then ſo heauy O my ſoule, and why art thou ſo diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eted within me? What man? Plucke vp a good heart: truſt in God: thinke vpon the honorable paſſion, and gladſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Chriſt. And then though thou wert neuer ſo much afflicted, yet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in the fiery furnace of affliction, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:174760:64"/>with ioy vnſpeakeable and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Daunce now, not as Herodias did, but as Dauid did. Leap vp in affection, as high as heauen. Where thou ſhalt heare one rapt vp to the third heauen, ſaying, to himſelfe, God forbid that I ſhoulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, reioyce in any thinge, but in the croſſe of Chriſt; and to vs, Reioyce in the Lord alwaies, and againe, I ſay, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce. And againe, and againe, I ſay, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, and reioyce, alwaies in the Lord. Eſpecially at this time. For if, when the matter was in doubt, &amp; no man almoſt knewe to what paſſe theſe troubles would ſort in the end, and very fewe in the church, no not the Apoſtles, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the virgin Mary did vnderſtand &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the reſurrection of Chriſt, yet then our Sauiour ſayd, VVEEP NOT FOR ME: how much more now ought wee not to weepe, but to reioyce, ſeeing our Lord hath ſo mightely declared himſelfe to be the ſonne of God<note n="(u)" place="margin">Rom. 1.4.</note>, by raiſing vp his owne ſelfe from the dead? And if wee might not weep when Iacob went ouer Iordan with nothing but his ſtaffe in his hand<note n="(x)" place="margin">Gen. 32.10.</note>, then much more nowe ought wee to lift vp our hearts in great ioy to
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:174760:64"/>God and ſay, O Lord we are not worthy of the leaſt of all thy mercyes: for our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>eſſed redeemer went ouer Iordan, with nothing but his croſſe, which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Iacobs ſtaffe<note n="(o)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Damaſcen. l <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>88.</hi>
               </note>, vpon his ſhoulder, but now hee is returned again with two greate troupes. O what a great troupe, what a goodly flock is here? wee with all the militant church are one flocke of Chriſt. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ftock is the triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phant church in heauen. With whom we muſt continually reioyce for the victory and the ſaluation which Chriſt hath ſhewed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s this day. For though on good friday towards euening the sky was red all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er coloured &amp; diſtained with the bloud of Chriſt<note n="(y)" place="margin">Mat. 16.2.</note>, yet laudes be to our Lord, O prayſed bee God, that was a good ſigne: this day it is fayre weather. The winter is nowe paſt: the raine is chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and gone: the flowers appeare in the earth: the time of the ſinging of birdes is come: and the voice of the Turtle is heard in our land<note n="(z)" place="margin">Cant. 2.11.</note>. And what ſaies the Turtle? Euen as it is here, VVEEP NOT FOR MEE. VVEEP NOT FOR ME, BVT VVEEP FOR YOVR SELVES. BVT VVEEP FOR YOVR SELVES. Pindarus reporteth there was an opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:174760:65"/>of the city of Rhodes, that golde rained downe vpon it<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Ode.</hi> 7.</note>. If euer gold did raine downe from heauen vpon any city, I thinke it is rather this city then Rhodes. Not only for aboundance of gold and worldly riches wherewith it is repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, but alſo much more for infinit ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall gifts, and golden graces of God. O London, London, excellent, excellent thinges are ſpoken of thee, O thou city of God! It is ſpoken of thee, that thou employeſt a great part of thy wealth to the reliefe of poore orphanes, of poore ſouldiers, of poore ſchollers. It is ſpoken of thee, that thou doeſt reuerence religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; loue the trueth more then any part of this realme doth beſides. It is ſpoken of thee, that none are more obedient, none more readie then thou art, both with bodie &amp; goods to defend the ſtate. It is ſpoken of thee, that thou art ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous in all foraine countries, that as A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s was called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Greece of Greece<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Athenaeus lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>, ſo London is called the England of England. And wee may almoſt as well ſay that al England is in London, as that all London is in England. Theſe are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent things, I aſſure you beloued, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent things indeede. Wherefore wee which haue receiued ſo many ſingular
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:174760:65"/>graces of God, ſhould aboue al other be thankfull for them. And not only one, or ſome few, but euen al of vs, ſhould bring forth good fruites, anſwerable to ſuch great mercies. Well, would to God it were ſo. But certainly it is not ſo. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly all amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs, all are not pure corne, there are many tares: all are not good fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, there are many bad: all are not wiſe virgins, there are many fooliſh: all are not ſheep, there are many goates. Yet to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ueigh particularly againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſins of this citie, which ſhuld make vs weep for our ſelues, I thinke it not greatly conuenient at this time. Only I beſeech you that we may trie and examine our ſelues: that wee may enter into our owne conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; euery one of vs humbly bowing the knees of his heart, and ſaying in this ſort, O Lord Ieſus, how haue I beſtowed all thoſe talents of gold which thou haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen mee? how haue I requited thee for all thy kindnes towards me? what hath my whole life been els but a continuall warring againſt thee? what hath it been els but a daily renewing of all thy blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die torments, and of thy whole paſſion? Ah vile wretch that I am, how ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue I like Iudas himſelfe betrayed thee, and
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:174760:66"/>ſold thee for a little worldly pleaſure, or for a little luker and gaine? how often haue I bound thy hands, and euen moſt deſpitefully ſpit in thy face, by refuſing thoſe gifts which thou wouldeſt haue giuen me, and by killing the comforts of thy Spirit? Woe is me, alacke for pitie, I am that curſed Cain which haue mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered innocent Abel my brother, whoſe bloud doth now cry out for vengeance againſt me, becauſe, that bloud by my ſinnes onely is polluted, by which the ſinnes of all the world beſides are pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. For this will I weepe day and night, yea though I had as many eyes in my head as there are ſtarres in the skye, yet I would weepe them out euery one<note n="(c)" place="margin">In ſontem frontem, atque in flumina lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina vertam.</note>, to thinke that I ſhould bee ſuch an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie wretch, as by my ſinnes to cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie Chriſt ſo often, and to put him to ſo many deaths, who hath been vnto me ſo kinde and ſo louing a Lord. O deare A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell, deare Abell! O my good brethren that I could poſſibly deuiſe what to ſay or what to doe, to obtaine thus much of you, or rather of God for you, that you would weepe, though it were neuer ſo little for your ſinnes. But alas, I can doe no more now, but commit and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend all that hath been ſpoken to the
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:174760:66"/>effectuall working of the holy Ghoſt in you, and to the faithfull obedience of your good hearts to God. Bleſſed bee God, I am yet very much reuiued (being otherwiſe almoſt quite ſpent with ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſo long) when I look about me and beholde euery one that is preſent. For I ſee no place in this great auditory, where there are not very many readie to weep, the water ſtanding in their eyes, &amp; ſome alreadie weeping right-out, in true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe and ſorrow for their ſinnes. You make me reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that which we reade in the booke of Iudges, when the Angel of the Lord found fault with the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites for their diſobedience, they lifted vp their voyces and wept, and called the name of that place Bochim, and offered vp ſacrifices there vnto the Lord<note n="(d)" place="margin">Iudg. 2.5.</note>. This place alſo may bee now called Bochim, that is, the place of weeping, wherein you haue offered vp as many ſacrifices to the Lord, as you haue ſhead teares for your ſelues. O what an acceptable ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to God is this your ſorrowful ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit? I warrant you, you ſhall neuer repent you of this repentance: you ſhall neuer be ſorrie for this ſorrowe. This ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſpirit of yours makes God haue a
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:174760:67"/>ioyfull ſpirit, and greatly pleaſes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights the holy Ghoſt. Wherefore now that we haue once made the good ſpirit of God reioyce and take pleaſure in vs, let vs not in any caſe hereafter, let vs not hereafter grieue the ſame ſpirit of God, whereby wee are now ſealed vp to the day of redemption. The holy Ghoſt is grieued when we are not grieued, but if we bee thus grieued for our ſinnes, then is the holy Ghoſt delighted. Yea ſuch griefe and ſorrow will not onely bee to the holy Ghoſt a great pleaſure and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, but alſo it wil be to vs the very ſeed or the intereſt and loane of euerlaſting life<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Baſ. Hom. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>144.</hi>
               </note>. For look how a father pitieth his owne childe, and if he ſee him crye, doth what he can to ſtill him, and takes out his handkercher, and wipes the infants eyes himſelfe: after the ſame faſhion God our heauenly father will with his owne holy finger wipe away all teares from our eyes, and take vs moſt louingly by the hand, and lead vs out of the houſe of mourning into the houſe of mirth. Then though wee haue ſowne in teares, yet wee ſhall reape in ioy<note n="f" place="margin">Tum breuibus lachrymis gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia long a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam. Paulinus.</note>. Yea though wee haue ſowne but a very few teares, which God hath in a ſmall bottle, yet we
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:174760:67"/>ſhall reape all the infinite ioyes which God hath in heauen. Then though wee haue wanted wine a little while, yet in the ende Chriſt ſhall turne all our water into wine, all our ſadnes into gladnes, all our muſing into muſicke, al our ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into ſinging. Then though wee haue been a long time married to wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping blear-eyd Leah, yet at length wee ſhall enioy the loue of cheerfull &amp; beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Rachell. Then ſhall Abraham that good mower bind vs vp into ſheaues as pure corne, and fill his boſome full with vs, and carrie vs into the Lords barne to make a ioyfull harueſt in heauen. Then ſhall wee with the wiſe virgins hauing ſtore of teares in our eyes, which are as oyle in our lampes, go out of this vale of teares, which floweth with woe &amp; wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, &amp; enter into the celeſtiall Canaan, which floweth with milke and honey. Then ſhall Chriſt ſay vnto vs, not as it is here, VVEEP NOT FOR ME, BVT VVEEP FOR YOVR SELVES: but hee ſhall ſaye, <hi>Weepe not for me, and weepe not for your ſelues.</hi> For that which would be too much ioy in this life, ſhall not be ioy enough in the life to come. Therefore he ſhall not only ſay vnto vs, <hi>Weepe not for mee, and weepe
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:174760:68"/>not for your ſelues:</hi> but he ſhall alſo ſay, <hi>Reioyce for mee, and reioyce for your ſelues. Reioyce for mee,</hi> becauſe I was once lower then the Angels, but now I am crowned with honour and glorie: <hi>and reioyce for your ſelues,</hi> becauſe you were once as ſheepe going aſtray, but now you are returned to the ſhepheard and biſhop of your ſoules. <hi>Reioyce. for me,</hi> becauſe I am your brother Ioſeph, whom once you ſolde into Egypt, but now all power is giuen me in heauen &amp; in earth: <hi>and reioyce for your ſelues,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you are the true children of Iſrael, which once dwelt in a land of famine, but now you are brought by triumpha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fierie chariots into the land of Goſhen, which is the kingdome of glorie. To the which kingdome of glorie, and ioy of all hands, ioy for Chriſt, ioy for our ſelues, we beſeech thee, O good Lord, to bring vs, after the miſerie of this wofull and wretched world, not for our owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts or merits, but for the moſt glorious paſſion, and moſt ioyfull reſurrection of Ieſus Chriſt, to whom, with the Father &amp; the holy Ghoſt, bee all honour and glorie, power &amp; praiſe, dignitie and dominion, now and euermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
